<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<book code="dost_gambler_enru">
	<bookInfo>
		<title>The Gambler</title>
		<lang>en</lang>
		<isTranslation>true</isTranslation>
		<totalChapters>17</totalChapters>
		<source>http://originalbook.ru/</source>
		<author>Fyodor Dostoevsky</author>
		<author translator="true">Richard Pevear</author>
		<author translator="true">Larissa Volokhonsky</author>
	</bookInfo>
	<content>
		<chapter num="1" name="CHAPTER I">
			<sentence num="1"> I’VE FINALLY COME BACK from my two week absence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">Our people have already been in Roulettenburg for three days.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">I thought they would be waiting for me God knows how eagerly, but I was mistaken.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">The general had an extremely independent look, spoke to me condescendingly, and sent me to his sister.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">It was clear they had got hold of money somewhere.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">It even seemed to me that the general was a little ashamed to look at me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">Marya Filippovna was extremely busy and scarcely spoke with me; she took the money, however, counted it, and listened to my whole report.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">Mezentsov, the little Frenchman, and some Englishman or other were expected for dinner; as usual, when there’s money, then at once it’s a formal dinner; Moscowstyle.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">Polina Alexandrovna, seeing me, asked what had taken me so long, and went off somewhere without waiting for an answer.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">Of course, she did it on purpose.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">We must have a talk, however.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">A lot has accumulated.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">I’ve been assigned a small room on the fourth floor of the hotel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">It’s known here that I belong to “But I don’t even have any money,” I said calmly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">“To lose it, you have to have it.” “You shall have it at once,” the general replied, blushing slightly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">He rummaged in his desk, consulted a ledger, and it turned out that he owed me about a hundred and twenty roubles.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">“How are we going to reckon it up?” he began.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">“It has to be converted into thalers. Here, take a hundred thalers, a round figure–the rest, of course, won’t get lost.” I silently took the money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">“Please don’t be offended by my words, you’re so touchy… If I made that observation, it was, so to speak, to warn you, and, of course, I have a certain right to do so… ” Coming back home with the children before dinner, I met a whole cavalcade.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">Our people had gone to have a look at some ruins. Two excellent carriages, magnificent horses! Mlle Blanche in the same carriage with Marya Filippovna and Polina; the little Frenchman, the Englishman, and the general on horseback.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">Passersby stopped and looked; an effect was produced; only it won’t come to any good for the general. I calculated that with the four thousand francs I had brought, plus whatever they had evidently managed to get hold of here, they now had seven or eight thousand francs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">That is too little for Mlle Blanche. Mlle Blanche is also staying in our hotel, along with her mother; our little Frenchman is here somewhere as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">The servants call him “M. le comte,” Mlle Blanche’s mother is called “Mme la comtesse”; well, maybe they really are comte and comtesse.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">I just knew that M. le comte would not recognize me when we gathered for dinner. The general, of course, did not even think of introducing us or of presenting me to him; and M. le comte himself has visited Russia and knows what small fry an I first met this strange Englishman in Prussia, on a train where we sat opposite each other, when I was catching up with our people; then I ran into him on entering France, and finally in Switzerland; twice in the course of these two weeks–and now I suddenly met him in Roulettenburg.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">Never in my life have I met a shyer man; he’s shy to the point of stupidity, and, of course, he knows it himself, because he’s not at all stupid. However, he’s very nice and quiet.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">I got him to talk at our first meeting in Prussia.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">He announced to me that he had been at Nordkap that summer, and that he would like very much to go to the Nizhny Novgorod fair.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">I don’t know how he became acquainted with the general; I believe he’s boundlessly in love with Polina. When she came in, he flushed a flaming crimson. He was very glad that I sat down beside him at the table, and it seems he considers me a bosom friend.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">At table the Frenchman set the tone extraordinarily; he was careless and pompous with everyone.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">And in Moscow, I remember, he just blew soap bubbles. He talked terribly much about finance and Russian politics.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">The general sometimes ventured to contradict–but modestly, only enough so as not to definitively damage his own importance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">I was in a strange state of mind. Of course, before dinner was halfthrough, I managed to ask myself my customary and habitual question: “How come I hang around with this general and didn’t leave them long, long ago?” Now and then I glanced at Polina Alexandrovna; she ignored me completely.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">It ended with me getting angry and deciding to be rude. It began with me suddenly, for no rhyme or reason, interfering in their conversation, loudly and without being asked.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">Above all, I wanted to quarrel with the little Frenchman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">I turned to the general and suddenly, quite loudly and distinctly, and, it seems, interrupting him, observed that in hotels this summer it was almost impossible for Russians to dine at the “If you’re a selfrespecting man,” I let myself go on, “you will unavoidably invite abuse and will have to put up with being exceedingly slighted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">In Paris, on the Rhine, even in Switzerland, there are so many little Poles and sympathizing little Frenchmen at the I said it in French. The general looked at me in perplexity, not knowing whether he should get angry or merely be astonished that I had forgotten myself so. “That means that somebody somewhere has taught you a lesson,” the little Frenchman said carelessly and contemptuously. “In Paris I began by quarreling with a Pole,” I replied, “then with a French officer who supported the Pole.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">And then some of the Frenchmen took my side, when I told them how I wanted to spit in the monseigneur’s coffee.” “Spit?” the general asked with pompous perplexity, and even looked around.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">The little Frenchman studied me mistrustfully. “Just so, sir,” I replied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">“Since I was convinced for a whole two days that I might have to go to Rome briefly to take care of our business, I went to the office of the Holy Father’s embassy in Paris to get a visa in my passport.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">{2} There I was met by a little abbé, about fifty years old, dry and with frost in his physiognomy, who, having heard me out politely, but extremely dryly, asked me to wait.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">Though I was in a hurry, I did sit down, of course, took out “ ‘What! Just when the cardinal is sitting with him!’ the abbé cried, recoiling from me in horror, rushed to the door, and spread his arms crosswise, showing that he would sooner die than let me pass.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">“Then I answered him that I was a heretic and a barbarian, ‘ “Really, though,” the general began… “What saved you was calling yourself a barbarian and a heretic,” the little Frenchman observed, grinning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“ “What, should I look to our Russians?</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">They sit here, don’t dare peep, and are ready, perhaps, to renounce the fact that they’re Russians. At any rate in my hotel in Paris they began to treat me with much greater attention when I told everybody about my fight with the abbé.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">The fat Polish “That cannot be,” the little Frenchman seethed, “a French soldier would not shoot a child!” “Yet so it was,” I replied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“It was told to me by a respectable retired captain, and I myself saw the scar from the bullet on his cheek.” The Frenchman began talking much and quickly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">The general tried to support him, but I recommended that he read, for instance, bits from the At first we began, naturally, with business.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">Polina simply became angry when I gave her only seven hundred guldens in all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">She was sure I’d bring her from Paris, in pawn for her diamonds, at least two thousand guldens or even more.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">“I need money at all costs,” she said, “and I must get it; otherwise I’m simply lost.” I started asking about what had happened in my absence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">“Nothing, except that we received two pieces of news from Petersburg, first, that grandmother was very unwell, and, two days later, that it seemed she had died.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">This was news from Timofei Petrovich,” Polina added, “and he’s a precise man. We’re waiting for the final, definitive news.” “So everyone here is in expectation?” I asked.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">“Of course: everyone and everything; for the whole six months that’s the only thing they’ve hoped for.” “And you’re hoping, too?” I asked.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">“Why, I’m not related to her at all, I’m only the general’s stepdaughter.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">But I know for certain that she’ll remember me in her will.” “It seems to me you’ll get a lot,” I said affirmatively. “Yes, she loved me; but why does it seem so to “Tell me,” I answered with a question, “our marquis, it seems, is also initiated into all the family secrets?” “And why are you interested in that?” asked Polina, giving me a stern and dry look.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">“Why not? If I’m not mistaken, the general has already managed to borrow money from him.” “You’ve guessed quite correctly.” “Well, would he lend him money if he didn’t know about grandma?</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">Did you notice, at dinner: three times or so, speaking about grandmother, he called her ‘grandma’–‘ “Yes, you’re right.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">As soon as he learns that I’m also getting something in the will, he’ll immediately propose to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">Is that what you wanted to find out?” “Only then? I thought he proposed a long time ago.” “You know perfectly well he hasn’t!” Polina said testily.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">“Where did you meet this Englishman?” she asked after a moment’s silence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">“I just knew you’d ask about him right away.” I told her about my previous meetings with Mr. Astley during my trip.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">“He’s shy and amorous and, of course, already in love with you?” “Yes, he’s in love with me,” Polina replied. “And he’s certainly ten times richer than the Frenchman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">What, does the Frenchman really have anything? Isn’t that open to doubt?” “No, it’s not. He has some sort of château.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">The general told me that yesterday. Well, so, is that enough for you?” “In your place, I’d certainly marry the Englishman.” “Why?” asked Polina. “The Frenchman’s handsomer, but he’s meaner; and the Englishman, on top of being honest, is also ten times richer,” I snapped.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">“Yes, but then the Frenchman is a marquis and more intelligent,” she replied with the greatest possible equanimity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">“Is that true?” I went on in the same way. “Perfectly.” Polina terribly disliked my questions, and I saw that she wanted to make me angry with her tone and the wildness of her answer.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">I told her so at once.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">“Why, it does indeed amuse me to see you in a fury.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">You ought to pay for the fact alone that I allow you to put such questions and make such surmises.” “I do indeed consider it my right to put all sorts of questions to you,” I replied calmly, “precisely because I’m prepared to pay for them however you like, and my own life I now count for nothing.” Polina burst out laughing: “Last time, on the Schlangenberg, you told me you were ready at my first word to throw yourself down headfirst, and I believe it’s a thousandfoot drop.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">One day I’ll speak that word, solely to see how you’re going to pay, and you may be sure I’ll stand firm.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">You are hateful to me–precisely because I’ve allowed you so much, and more hateful still, because I need you so much.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">But for the time being I do need you–I must take good care of you.” She went to get up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">She had spoken with irritation. Lately she has always finished a conversation with me with spite and irritation, with real spite.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">“Allow me to ask you, what is this Mlle Blanche?” I asked, not wanting to let her go without an explanation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">“You know yourself what Mlle Blanche is. Nothing more has been added.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">Mlle Blanche will probably become Madame la Générale–naturally, if the rumor of grandmother’s death is confirmed, because Mlle Blanche, and her mother, and her second cousin, the marquis, all know very well that we are ruined.” “And the general is definitively in love?” “That’s not the point now.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">Listen and remember: take these seven hundred florins and go gambling, win me as much as you can at roulette; I need money now at all costs.” Having said this, she called Nadenka and went to the vauxhall, where she joined our whole company.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">I, however, turned into the first path to the left, pondering and astonished.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">It was as if I’d been hit on the head, after the order to go and play roulette.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">Strange thing: I had enough to ponder, and yet I immersed myself wholly in an analysis of my feelings for Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">Really, it had been easier for me during those two weeks of absence than now, on the day of my return, though on the way I had longed for her like a madman, had thrashed about like a man in a frenzy, and even in sleep had seen her before me every moment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">Once (this was in Switzerland), I had fallen asleep on the train, and it seems I began talking aloud with Polina, which made all my fellow travelers laugh.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">And now once more I asked myself the question: do I love her?</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">And once more I was unable to answer it, that is, better to say, I answered myself again, for the hundredth time, that I hated her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">Yes, she was hateful to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">There were moments (and precisely each time at the end of our conversations) when I would have given half my life to strangle her!</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">I swear, if it had been possible to sink a sharp knife slowly into her breast, it seems to me I’d have snatched at it with delight.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">And yet, I swear by all that’s holy, if on the Schlangenberg, on the fashionable However, I had her commission–to win at roulette at all costs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">There was no time to reflect on why and how soon I had to win, and what new considerations had been born in that eternally calculating head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">Besides, during these two weeks, evidently, no end of new facts had accrued, of which I still had no idea.</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">All this had to be figured out, it all had to be grasped, and as soon as possible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">But meanwhile now there was no time: I had to go to the roulette table.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="2" name="CHAPTER II">
			<sentence num="1"> I CONFESS, THIS WAS unpleasant for me. Though I had decided that I would play, it was not at all my intention to begin by playing for others.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">It even threw me off somewhat, and I went into the gaming rooms with a most vexatious feeling.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">At first sight, I disliked everything there.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">I can’t stand this lackeyishness in the gossip columns of the whole world, and mainly in our Russian newspapers, where almost every spring our columnists tell about two things: first, the extraordinary magnificence and splendor of the gaming rooms in the roulette towns on the Rhine, and second, the heaps of gold that supposedly lie on the tables.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">They’re not paid for that; they simply do it out of disinterested obsequiousness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">There is no magnificence in these trashy rooms, and as for the gold, not only are there no heaps on the tables, but there’s scarcely even the slightest trace.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">Of course, now and then during the season some odd duck suddenly turns up, an Englishman, or some sort of Asiatic, a Turk, as happened this summer, and suddenly loses or wins a great deal; the rest all play for small change, and, on the average, there’s usually very little money lying on the table.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">As I had only just entered the gaming room (for the first time in my life), I did not venture to play for a while.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">Besides, it was crowded.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">But if I had been alone, even then I think I would sooner have left than started playing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">I confess, my heart was pounding, and I was not coolheaded; I knew for certain and had long resolved that I would not leave Roulettenburg just so; something radical and definitive was bound to happen in my fate.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">So it must be, and so it would be.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Ridiculous as it is that I should expect to get so much from roulette, it seems to me that the routine opinion, accepted by all, that it is stupid and absurd to expect anything at all from gambling, is even more ridiculous.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">Why is gambling worse than any other way of making money–trade, for instance?</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">It’s true that only one in a hundred wins.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">But what do I care about that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">In any case, I decided to look on at first and not start anything serious that evening.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">That evening, if something did happen, it would be accidental and slight–and that’s what I settled on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">Besides, I had to study the game itself; because, despite the thousands of descriptions of roulette I had always read with such avidity, I understood decidedly nothing of how it worked until I saw it myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">First, it all seemed so filthy to me–somehow morally nasty and filthy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">I am by no means speaking of those greedy and restless faces that stand in dozens, even in hundreds, around the gaming tables.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">I see decidedly nothing filthy in the desire to win sooner and more; I have always found very stupid the thought of one wellnourished and prosperous moralist, who, in response to someone’s excuse that “they play for low stakes,” replied: so much the worse, because there’s little interest.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">As if little interest and big interest were not the same.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">It’s a matter of proportion.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">What’s small for Rothschild, is great wealth for me, and as for gains and winnings–people everywhere, not only at the roulette table, do nothing but gain or win something from each other.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">Whether gain and profit are vile in themselves–is another question.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">But I won’t decide it here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Since I myself was possessed in the highest degree by a desire to win, all this interest and all this interested filth, if you wish, was for me, as I entered the room, somehow the more helpful, the more congenial.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">It’s really nice when people don’t stand on ceremony, but act in an open and unbuttoned way with each other.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">And why should one deceive oneself?</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">It’s the most futile and illcalculated occupation!</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Especially unattractive, at first sight, in all this roulette riffraff was the respect for what they were doing, the grave and even deferential way they all stood around the tables.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">That’s why there is a sharp distinction here between the kind of gambling known as The riffraff do indeed play very filthily.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">I’m even not averse to the thought that a lot of the most common thievery goes on here at the table.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">The croupiers who sit at the ends of the table, look after the stakes, and make the payments, have a terrible amount of work.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">There’s more riffraff for you!</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">For the most part they’re Frenchmen.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">However, I’m observing and making remarks here not at all in order to describe roulette; I’m attuning myself, in order to know how to behave in the future.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">I noticed, for instance, that there was nothing more ordinary than for someone’s hand suddenly to reach out from behind the table and take what you’ve won.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">An argument begins, there’s often shouting, and–I humbly ask you to prove, to find witnesses, that the stake is yours!</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">At first this was all Chinese to me; I only guessed and figured out somehow that one can stake on numbers, odds and evens, and colors.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">That evening I decided to try a hundred guldens of Polina Alexandrovna’s money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">The thought that I was setting out to play for someone else somehow threw me off.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">The sensation was extremely unpleasant, and I wanted to be done with it quickly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">I kept fancying that by starting out for Polina I was undermining my own luck.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">Is it really impossible to touch a gaming table without being infected at once with superstition?</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">I began by taking out five friedrichs d’or, that is, fifty guldens, and staking them on evens.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">The wheel spun and it came up thirteen–I lost.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">With some morbid feeling, solely to be done with it somehow and leave, I staked another five friedrichs d’or on red.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">It came up red.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">I staked all ten friedrichs d’or–again it came up red.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">I again staked it all at once, and again it came up red.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">I took the forty friedrichs d’or and staked twenty on the twelve middle numbers, not knowing what would come of it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">I was paid triple.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">Thus, from ten friedrichs d’or, I had suddenly acquired eighty.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Some extraordinary and strange sensation made it so unbearable for me that I decided to leave.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">It seemed to me that I would play quite differently if I were playing for myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">Nevertheless, I staked all eighty friedrichs d’or once more on evens.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">This time it came up four; they poured out another eighty friedrichs d’or for me, and, taking the whole heap of a hundred and sixty friedrichs d’or, I went to look for Polina Alexandrovna.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">They had all gone for a stroll somewhere in the park, and I managed to see her only at supper.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">This time the Frenchman wasn’t there, and the general made a display of himself; among other things, he found it necessary to observe to me again that he did not wish to see me at the gaming table.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">In his opinion, it would be very compromising for him if I somehow lost too much; “but even if you were to win a lot, then, too, I would be compromised,” he added significantly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">“Of course, I have no right to control your actions, but you must agree… ” Here, as usual, he didn’t finish.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">I answered dryly that I had very little money and that, consequently, I could not lose too conspicuously, even if I should gamble.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">On the way to my room upstairs, I managed to hand Polina her winnings and declared to her that I would not play for her another time.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">“Why not?” she asked anxiously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">“Because I want to play for myself,” I replied, studying her with astonishment, “and this hampers me.” “So you resolutely go on being convinced that roulette is your salvation and your only way out?” she asked mockingly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">I answered again very seriously that, yes; that as for my absolute assurance of winning, let it be ridiculous, I agree, “so long as I’m left alone.” Polina Alexandrovna insisted that I absolutely must share today’s winnings half and half with her, and wanted to give me eighty friedrichs d’or, suggesting that we go on playing in the future on that condition.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">I refused the half resolutely and definitively, and declared that I could not play for others, not because I didn’t want to, but because I was sure to lose.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">“However, I myself, stupid as it may be, also hope almost only in roulette,” she said pensively.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">“And therefore you absolutely must go on playing half and half with me, and–of course–you will.” Here she left me, not listening to my further objections.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="3" name="CHAPTER III">
			<sentence num="1"> HOWEVER, FOR THE whole day yesterday she didn’t say a word to me about gambling.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">And she generally avoided talking with me yesterday.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">Her earlier manner with me did not change.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">The same complete carelessness of attitude when we met, and even something scornful and hateful.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">Generally she doesn’t wish to conceal her loathing for me; I can see that.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">In spite of that, she also doesn’t conceal from me that she needs me for something and is saving me for something.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">Some sort of strange relations have been established between us, in many ways incomprehensible to me–considering her pride and arrogance with everyone.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">She knows, for instance, that I love her madly, she even allows me to speak of my passion–and, of course, she could in no way express her scorn of me more fully than by this permission to speak to her of my love unhindered and uncensored.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">“Meaning,” so to say, “I hold your feelings of so little account that it is decidedly all the same to me what you speak to me about and what you feel for me.” Of her own affairs she talked a lot with me before as well, but she was never fully candid.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">What’s more, there were the following subtleties in her disregard for me: she knows, let’s say, that I’m aware of some circumstance of her life or of something that troubles her greatly; she will even tell me something of her circumstances herself, if she needs to use me somehow for her own purposes, like a slave, or for running errands; but she will always tell me exactly as much as someone needs to know who is used for running errands, and–if the whole sequence of events is still unknown to me, if she sees herself how I suffer and worry over her sufferings and worries, she will never deign to set me fully at ease by friendly candor, though, as she often employed me on not only troublesome but even dangerous errands, she was obliged, in my opinion, to be candid with me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">And was it worth caring about my feelings, about the fact that I also worried, and maybe cared and suffered three times more over her cares and misfortunes than she did herself?</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">Three weeks ago I already knew of her intention to play roulette.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">She even warned me that I was to play in her place, because it was indecent for her to play.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">By the tone of her words I noticed then that she had some serious concern, and not merely a wish to win money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">What was money in itself to her!</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">There’s a goal here, some circumstance that I may guess at, but that I don’t yet know.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">Of course, the humiliation and slavery in which she holds me could give me (quite often do give me) the possibility of questioning her crudely and directly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">Since I’m a slave to her and all too insignificant in her eyes, there is no point in her being offended at my crude curiosity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">But the thing is that, while she allows me to ask questions, she doesn’t answer them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">Sometimes she doesn’t notice them at all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">That’s how it is with us!</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">Yesterday there was a lot of talk among us about a telegram sent to Petersburg four days ago and to which there has been no reply.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">The general is visibly worried and pensive.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">It has to do, of course, with grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">The Frenchman is worried as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">Yesterday, for instance, they had a long and serious talk after dinner.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">The Frenchman’s tone with us all was extraordinarily arrogant and careless.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Even with Polina he was careless to the point of rudeness; however, he enjoys taking part in general strolls in the vauxhall or in cavalcades and drives out of town.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">I have long been informed of some of the circumstances binding the Frenchman and the general: in Russia they were going to start a factory together; I don’t know whether their project has fallen through or they’re still talking about it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">Besides that, I chanced to learn part of a family secret: the Frenchman actually helped the general out last year and gave him thirty thousand to make up a deficit in government funds as he handed over his post.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">And so, of course, the general is in his clutches; but now, right now, the main role in all this is being played all the same by Mlle Blanche, and in that I’m sure I’m not mistaken.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Who is Mlle Blanche?</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">Among us here they say she’s a French noblewoman, who goes around with her mother and has a colossal fortune.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">It is also known that she is some sort of relation of our marquis, only a very distant one, some sort of cousin or second cousin.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">They say that before my trip to Paris, contacts between the Frenchman and Mlle Blanche were somehow much more ceremonious, they seemed to be on a much more refined and delicate footing; while now their acquaintance, friendship, and family connection have emerged as somehow more coarse, more intimate.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">Maybe our situation seems so bad to them that they no longer find it necessary to be too ceremonious with us and to hide things.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">I noticed two days ago how Mr. Astley was studying Mlle Blanche and her mother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">It seemed to me that he knew them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">It even seemed to me that our Frenchman had met Mr. Astley previously as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">However, Mr. Astley is so shy, prudish, and reserved that one can virtually count on him–he won’t wash any dirty linen in public.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">The Frenchman, at any rate, barely greets him and almost doesn’t look at him; which means he’s not afraid of him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">That’s understandable; but why is it that Mlle Blanche almost doesn’t look at him either?</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">The more so as yesterday the marquis let something slip: in general conversation he suddenly said, I don’t remember on what occasion, that Mr. Astley was colossally rich and he knew it for a fact; and so Mlle Blanche might well look at Mr. Astley!</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">The general is now thoroughly worried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">It’s clear what a telegram about his aunt’s death could mean for him now!</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">Though it seemed certain to me that Polina was avoiding conversation with me, as if on purpose, I myself assumed a cold and indifferent air as well: I kept thinking she was just about to approach me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">Instead, yesterday and today I turned all my attention predominantly to Mlle Blanche.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">The poor general, he’s utterly lost!</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">To fall in love with such strong passion at the age of fiftyfive is of course a misfortune.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">Add to that his widowerhood, his children, his completely ruined estate, his debts, and, finally, the woman he had to fall in love with.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">Mlle Blanche is quite beautiful.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">But I don’t know whether I’ll be understood if I say that hers is one of those faces that can be frightening.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">At any rate I have always been afraid of such women.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">She must be about twentyfive.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">She is tall and well built, with shapely shoulders; her neck and bosom are luxuriant; her complexion is a swarthy yellow; her hair is black as ink, and there is a terrible amount of it, enough for two coiffures.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Her eyes are black, the whites are yellowish, her gaze is insolent, her teeth are very white, her lips always rouged; she smells of musk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">She dresses showily, richly, with I also found Mr. Astley curious yesterday and today.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">Yes, I’m convinced that he is in love with Polina!</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">It’s curious and ridiculous how much the gaze of a prudish and painfully chaste man, touched by love, can sometimes express, and that precisely at a moment when the man would, of course, sooner be glad to fall through the earth than say or express anything with a word or a look.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">We run into Mr. Astley very often during our walks.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">He doffs his hat and passes by, dying, naturally, from the desire to join us. If he’s invited, he immediately declines.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">At resting places, in the vauxhall, at a concert, or near the fountain, he unfailingly stops somewhere not far from our bench, and wherever we may be, in the park, in the woods, or on the Schlangenberg–you need only raise your eyes, look around, and unfailingly somewhere, on the nearest path, or behind a bush, a little corner of Mr. Astley will appear.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">He seems to be seeking an occasion to speak with me privately.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">This morning we met and exchanged a couple of words. He sometimes speaks somehow extremely abruptly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Without even a “good morning,” he began by declaring: “Ah, Mlle Blanche!… I’ve seen many women like Mlle Blanche!” He fell silent, looking at me significantly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">What he wanted to say by that, I don’t know, because when I asked him what it meant, he nodded with a sly smile and added: “Quite so.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">Is Mlle Pauline very fond of flowers?” “I don’t know, I simply don’t know,” I replied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">“What? You don’t know that either?” he cried in great amazement.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">“I don’t know, I simply never noticed,” I repeated, laughing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">“Hm, that gives me a particular thought.” Here he nodded and walked on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">He looked pleased, however. We speak to each other in the most vile French.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="4" name="CHAPTER IV">
			<sentence num="1"> TODAY WAS A RIDICULOUS, outrageous, absurd day.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">Now it’s eleven o’clock at night.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">I’m sitting in my little room and remembering.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">It started with my having to go in the morning and play roulette for Polina Alexandrovna.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">I took all her hundred and sixty friedrichs d’or, but on two conditions: first, that I did not want to go halves, that is, if I won, I’d take nothing for myself; and second, that in the evening Polina would explain to me precisely why she has such a need to win and precisely how much money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">I still can in no way suppose that it is simply for the sake of money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">Money is obviously necessary here, and as soon as possible, for some particular purpose.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">She promised to explain, and I went.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">There was a terrible crowd in the gaming rooms.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">How insolent they all are, and how greedy!</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">I pushed my way to the middle and stood right next to the croupier; then I began timidly to play, staking two or three coins.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">Meanwhile I observed and took note; it seemed to me that calculation meant rather little in itself and had none of the importance many gamblers attach to it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">They sit with ruled sheets of paper, note down the stakes, calculate, deduce the chances, reckon up, finally place their bet, and–lose in exactly the same way as we simple mortals, who play without calculation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">But, on the other hand, I drew one conclusion that seems to be correct: in the sequence of accidental chances, there is indeed, if not a system, at any rate the semblance of some order–which, of course, is very strange.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">For instance, it happens that after the twelve middle numbers come the twelve last ones; twice, let’s say, the ball lands on these twelve last ones, and then goes on to the twelve first.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">Having landed on the twelve first, it goes on again to the twelve middle numbers, lands three or four times on the twelve middle ones, then again goes on to the twelve last, from where again, after landing twice, it goes on to the first, lands there once, goes on to land three times on the middle ones, and so it continues for an hour and a half, for two hours.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">One, three, and two; one, three, and two.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">It’s very amusing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">One day or one morning it goes, for instance, so that red alternates with black and vice versa, every moment almost without any order, so that the ball doesn’t land on the same color more than two or three times in a row.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">But the next day, or the next evening, it happens, for instance, that it lands on red alone up to twentytwo times in a row, and it’s sure to go on that way for some time–a whole day, for instance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">A lot of this was explained to me by Mr. Astley, who spent the whole morning at the gaming tables, but did not stake once himself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">As for me, I lost everything, and very quickly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">I straight away staked twenty friedrichs d’or on evens and won, staked five and won again, and so it went two or three more times.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">I think about four hundred friedrichs d’or came into my hands in some five minutes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">I should have walked away right then, but some strange sensation was born in me, some defiance of fate, some desire to give it a flick, to stick my tongue out at it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">I placed the biggest stake permitted, four thousand guldens, and lost.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">Then, getting excited, I took out all I had left, staked it in the same way, and lost again, after which I left the table as if stunned.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">I didn’t even understand what had happened to me, and announced my loss to Polina Alexandrovna only just before dinner.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">The time till then I spent loitering in the park.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">At dinner I was again in an agitated state, just as three days ago.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">The Frenchman and Mlle Blanche were again dining with us.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">It turned out that Mlle Blanche had been in the gaming rooms that morning and had seen my exploits.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">This time she talked with me somehow more attentively.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">The Frenchman was more straightforward and simply asked me if I had really gambled away my own money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">It seems to me he suspects Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">In short, there’s something there.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">I lied at once and said it was my money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">The general was extremely surprised: where had I gotten so much money?</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">I explained that I had begun with ten friedrichs d’or, that six or seven wins in a row, doubled, gained me five or six thousand guldens, and that I had then lost it all in two turns.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">All that, of course, was probable.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">While explaining it, I looked at Polina, but could make out nothing in her face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">However, she let me lie and did not correct me; from that I concluded that I did have to lie and conceal that I was playing for her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">In any case, I thought to myself, she owed me an explanation and this morning had promised to reveal something or other to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">I thought the general would make some remark, but he kept silent; instead I noticed worry and uneasiness in his face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">Maybe, in his tough circumstances, it was simply hard for him to hear that such a respectable pile of gold had come and gone in a quarter of an hour for such a wasteful fool as me. I suspect that a heated controversy had taken place between him and the Frenchman yesterday evening.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">They had locked themselves in and talked hotly about something for a long time.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">The Frenchman had come out looking vexed at something, and early this morning had gone to the general again–probably in order to continue yesterday’s conversation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">Hearing of my loss, the Frenchman observed to me caustically and even spitefully that I ought to be more sensible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">He added, I don’t know why, that while many Russians gamble, in his opinion, Russians are incapable even of gambling.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">“And in my opinion, roulette is just made for Russians,” I said, and when the Frenchman smirked scornfully at my response, I observed to him that, of course, the truth was on my side, because, in speaking of Russians as gamblers, I was abusing them much more than praising them, and that meant I could be believed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">“On what do you base your opinion?” asked the Frenchman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">“On the fact that the ability to acquire capital entered the catechism of virtues and merits of the civilized Western man historically and almost as the main point.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">While a Russian is not only incapable of acquiring capital, but even wastes it somehow futilely and outrageously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">Nevertheless, we Russians also need money,” I added, “and therefore we are very glad of and very prone to such methods as, for instance, roulette, where one can get rich suddenly, in two hours, without any work.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">We find that very attractive; but since we also gamble futilely, without working at it, we lose!” “That is partly true,” the Frenchman observed smugly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">“No, it’s not true, and it’s shameful to speak that way of your fatherland,” the general observed sternly and imposingly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">“For pity’s sake,” I answered him, “is it really not clear yet which is more vile–Russian outrageousness, or the German way of accumulation through honest work?” “What an outrageous thought!” exclaimed the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">“What a Russian thought!” exclaimed the Frenchman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">I laughed, I wanted terribly to egg them on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">“And I’d rather spend all my life roaming about in a Kirghiz tent,” I cried, “than worship a German idol.” “What idol?” cried the general, beginning to get seriously angry.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">“The German way of accumulating wealth.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">I haven’t been here long, but, nevertheless, all the same, what I’ve managed to observe and verify here arouses the indignation of my Tartar blood.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">By God, I don’t want such virtues!</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">I managed to make a sevenmile tour here yesterday.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Well, it’s exactly the same as in those moralizing little German picture books: everywhere here each house has its “Now, don’t be angry, General, let me tell it as touchingly as possible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">I myself remember my late father reading such books aloud to me and my mother in the evenings, under the lindens, in the front garden… I can judge it properly myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">Well, so every such family here is in total slavery and obedience to a “I don’t know if there’s much truth in what you’ve said,” the general observed pensively, “but I know for certain that you begin showing off insufferably as soon as you’re allowed to forget yourself the least bit… ” As was usual with him, he did not finish what he was saying.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">If our general began speaking about something just a bit more significant than ordinary conversation, he never finished.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">The Frenchman listened carelessly, goggling his eyes slightly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">He understood almost nothing of what I said. Polina looked on with some sort of haughty indifference. It seemed she heard nothing that was said, not only by me, but by anyone else at the table this time.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="5" name="CHAPTER V">
			<sentence num="1"> SHE WAS UNUSUALLY PENSIVE, but as soon as we left the table, she told me to accompany her on a walk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">We took the children and went to the fountain in the park.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">As I was particularly agitated, I blurted out a question stupidly and crudely: why is it that our marquis des Grieux, the little Frenchman, not only doesn’t accompany her now, when she goes out somewhere, but doesn’t even speak to her for whole days at a time?</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">“Because he’s a scoundrel,” she answered strangely.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">I had never before heard such an opinion about des Grieux from her, and I kept silent, afraid to understand this irritability.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">“And did you notice that he’s not on good terms with the general today?” “You want to know what’s the matter?” she answered dryly and irritably.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">“You do know that the general is entirely mortgaged to him, everything he owns is his, and if grandmother doesn’t die, the Frenchman immediately comes into possession of all that’s mortgaged to him.” “Ah, so it’s really true that everything’s mortgaged?</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">I’d heard, but didn’t know it was decidedly everything.” “But of course!” “And with that it’s goodbye Mlle Blanche,” I observed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">“She won’t be a generaless then!</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">You know what: it seems to me the general is so in love that he might shoot himself if Mlle Blanche abandons him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">At his age it’s dangerous to be so in love.” “I think myself that something will happen to him,” Polina Alexandrovna observed pensively.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">“And how splendid that is,” I cried. “She couldn’t show more crudely that she had consented to marry only for money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Here even decencies weren’t observed, it all happened quite without ceremony. A wonder!</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">And as for grandmother, what could be more comical and filthy than to send telegram after telegram, asking: ‘Is she dead, is she dead?’ Eh?</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">How do you like it, Polina Alexandrovna?” “That’s all nonsense,” she said with disgust, interrupting me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">“On the contrary, I’m astonished that you’re in such a merry mood.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">What are you glad about?</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">Can it be because you lost my money?” “Why did you give it to me to lose?</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">I told you I couldn’t play for others, the less so for you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">I’ll obey whatever orders you give me; but the result doesn’t depend on me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">I warned you that nothing would come of it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">Tell me, are you very crushed to have lost so much money?</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">What do you need so much for?” “Why these questions?” “But you yourself promised me to explain… Listen: I’m perfectly convinced that when I start playing for myself (I have twelve friedrichs d’or), I’ll win.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">Then take as much as you need from me.” She made a scornful face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">“Don’t be angry with me,” I went on, “for such an offer.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">I’m so pervaded by the awareness that I’m a zero before you, that is, in your eyes, that you can even accept money from me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">A present from me cannot offend you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Besides, I lost yours.” She gave me a quick glance and, noticing that I was speaking irritably and sarcastically, changed the subject again: “There’s nothing interesting for you in my circumstances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">If you want to know, I simply owe the money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">I borrowed money and would like to pay it back.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">I had the crazy and strange notion that I was sure to win here at the gaming table.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Why I had that notion I don’t understand, but I believed in it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">Who knows, maybe I believed because I had no other choice.” “Or because there was all too much Polina was surprised.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">“Why,” she asked, “aren’t you hoping for the same thing yourself?</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">Two weeks ago you yourself once spoke to me, a lot and at length, about your being fully convinced of winning here at roulette, and tried to persuade me not to look at you as a madman–or were you joking then?</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">But I remember you spoke so seriously that it couldn’t possibly have been taken for a joke.” “That’s true,” I answered pensively.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">“To this day I’m fully convinced of winning. I’ll even confess to you that you’ve just now led me to a question: precisely why has my senseless and outrageous loss today not left me with any doubts? I’m still fully convinced that as soon as I start playing for myself, I’m sure to win.” “Why are you so completely certain?” “If you like–I don’t know.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">I know only that I “Which means you also have all too much “I’ll bet you doubt I’m capable of feeling a serious need.” “It’s all the same to me,” Polina replied quietly and indifferently.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">“If you like– “By the way,” I interrupted, “you said you had to repay a debt. A nice debt, then! Not to the Frenchman?” “What are these questions? You’re particularly sharp today.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">You’re not drunk, are you?” “You know I allow myself to say anything and sometimes ask very frank questions.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">I repeat, I am your slave, one is not ashamed with slaves, and a slave cannot give offense.” “That’s all rubbish!</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">And I can’t stand this ‘slave’ theory of yours!” “Note that I speak of my slavery not because I wish to be your slave, but just so–as of a fact that does not depend on me at all.” “Tell me straight out, why do you need money?” “And why do you want to know that?” “As you like,” she replied and proudly tossed her head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“You can’t stand the slave theory, but you demand slavery: ‘Answer and don’t argue!’ Very well, so be it. Why money, you ask?</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">What do you mean, why? Money’s everything!” “I understand, but not falling into such madness from desiring it!</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">You also reach the point of frenzy, of fatalism! There’s something in it, some special goal.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">Speak without meandering, I want it that way.” It was as if she was beginning to get angry, and I liked terribly that she put so much heart into her questioning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">“Of course there’s a goal,” I said, “but I’m unable to explain what it is. No more than that with money I’ll become a different person for you, and not a slave.” “What?</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">How are you going to achieve that?” “How achieve it?</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">What, you don’t even understand how I can achieve that you look at me otherwise than as a slave?</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">Well, that’s just what I don’t want, such surprises and perplexities.” “You said this slavery was a pleasure for you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">I thought so myself.” “You thought so,” I cried with some strange pleasure.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">“Ah, how good such naïveté is coming from you!</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">Well, yes, yes, to be enslaved to you is a pleasure. There is, there is pleasure in the ultimate degree of humiliation and insignificance!” I went on raving.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">“Devil knows, maybe there is in the knout, too, when the knout comes down on your back and tears your flesh to pieces… But may be I want to try other pleasures as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">Earlier at the table, in your presence, the general read me a lesson, because of the seven hundred roubles a year which I still may not even get from him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">The marquis des Grieux raises his eyebrows, scrutinizes me, and at the same time doesn’t notice me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">And maybe I, for my part, passionately desire to take the marquis des Grieux by the nose in your presence?” “A milksop’s talk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">One can behave with dignity in any situation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">If there’s a struggle involved, it’s elevating, not humiliating.” “Straight out of a copybook! Just try to suppose that I may not know how to behave with dignity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">That is, perhaps I’m a dignified man, but I don’t know how to behave with dignity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">Do you understand that it may be so? All Russians are that way, and you know why?</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">Because Russians are too richly and multifariously endowed to be able to find a decent form for themselves very quickly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">It’s a matter of form. For the most part, we Russians are so richly endowed that it takes genius for us to find a decent form.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Well, but most often there is no genius, because generally it rarely occurs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">It’s only the French, and perhaps some few other Europeans, who have so welldefined a form that one can look extremely dignified and yet be a most undignified man.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">That’s why form means so much to them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">A Frenchman can suffer an insult, a real, heartfelt insult, and not wince, but a flick on the nose he won’t suffer for anything, because it’s a violation of the accepted and timehonored form of decency.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">That’s why our young ladies fall so much for Frenchmen, because they have good form. In my opinion, however, there’s no form there, but only a rooster, “Maybe that’s why you count on buying me with money,” she said, “since you don’t believe in my nobility?” “When did I ever count on buying you with money?” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">“Your tongue ran away with you and you lost your thread. If it’s not me, it’s my respect you think you can buy with money.” “Well, no, that’s not so at all. I told you, it’s hard for me to explain.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">You intimidate me. Don’t be angry at my babbling. You see why it’s impossible to be angry with me: I’m simply mad.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">But, anyhow, it’s all the same to me if you are angry. When I’m upstairs in my little room, I only have to remember and imagine the rustle of your dress, and I’m ready to bite my hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">And why are you angry with me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">Because I call myself a slave? Avail yourself, avail yourself of my slavery, avail yourself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">Someday I’ll kill you, do you know that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">Not because I’ve fallen out of love or become jealous, but–just so, simply kill you, because I sometimes long to eat you up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">You’re laughing… ” “I’m not laughing at all,” she said with wrath. “I order you to be silent.” She stopped, barely able to breathe from wrath.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">By God, I don’t know whether she was goodlooking or not, but I always liked looking at her when she stood before me like that, and so I often liked to provoke her wrath.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">I told her that.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">“What filth!” she exclaimed with disgust. “It makes no difference to me,” I went on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">“Do you know, too, that it’s dangerous for us to go about together: many times I’ve had an irrepressible longing to beat you, to mutilate you, to strangle you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">And what do you think, won’t it come to that? You’ll drive me to delirium. Am I afraid of a scandal? Of your wrath?</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">What is your wrath to me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">I love without hope, and I know that after that I’ll love you a thousand times more. If I ever kill you, I’ll have to kill myself, too; well, so–I’ll put off killing myself for as long as I can, in order to feel this unbearable pain of being without you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">Do you know an incredible thing: I love you “What stupid babble!” she cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">“It’s none of my affair whether it’s stupid or intelligent,” I cried. “I know that in your presence I have to talk, talk, talk–and so I talk. I lose all selfrespect in your presence, and it makes no difference to me.” “Why should I make you jump off the Schlangenberg?” she said dryly and somehow especially offensively.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">“It would be completely useless to me.” “Splendid!” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">“You said that splendid ‘useless’ on purpose, in order to intimidate me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">I see right through you. Useless, you say? But pleasure is always useful, and wild, boundless power–if only over a fly–is also a pleasure of a certain sort.</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">Man is a despot by nature and likes to play the torturer. You like it terribly.” I remember she studied me with some especially close attention.</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">It must be that my face then expressed all my senseless and absurd feelings.</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">I recall now that our conversation actually went on like that almost word for word, as I’ve described it here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">My eyes were bloodshot. Froth clotted on the edges of my lips.</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">And as for the Schlangenberg, I swear on my honor even now: if she had ordered me to throw myself down then, I would have done it!</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">If she had said it only as a joke, said it with contempt, spitting on me–even then I would have jumped!</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">“No, why, I believe you,” she said, but as only she knows how to speak sometimes, with such contempt and sarcasm, with such arrogance, that, by God, I could have killed her at that moment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">She was taking a risk. I also wasn’t lying about that, talking to her. “Are you a coward?” she asked me suddenly. “I don’t know, maybe I am.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">I don’t know… I haven’t thought about it for a long time.” “If I told you: kill this man, would you kill him?” “Who?” “Whoever I wanted.” “The Frenchman?” “Don’t ask, answer–whoever I point to.</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">I want to know whether you were speaking seriously just now.” She waited so seriously and impatiently for my reply that I felt somehow strange. “But will you tell me, finally, what’s going on here?” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">“Are you afraid of me, or what? I myself can see all the disorders here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">You’re the stepdaughter of a ruined and crazy man, infected with a passion for that shedevil–Blanche; then there’s this Frenchman with his mysterious influence over you, and–now you ask me so seriously… such a question.</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">At any rate let me know: otherwise I’ll go mad right here and do something. Or are you ashamed to honor me with your candor? Can you really be ashamed with me?” “I’m not talking about that at all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">I asked you and I’m waiting for a reply.” “Of course I’ll kill,” I cried, “whoever you order me to, but can you really… would you really order that?” “What do you think, that I’ll feel sorry for you?</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">I’ll order you to do it, and stay out of it myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">Can you bear that? No, how could you! You might kill on orders and then come and kill me for having dared to send you.” It was as if something hit me on the head at these words.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">Of course, even then I considered her question half as a joke, as a challenge; but all the same she said it much too seriously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">All the same, I was struck by her speaking it out like that, by her having such a right over me, accepting such power over me, and saying so directly: “Go to your ruin, and I’ll stay out of it.” There was something so cynical and frank in these words that, in my opinion, it was far too much.</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">So that’s how she looks at me then? This was going beyond the bounds of slavery and nonentity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">To have such a view is to raise a man to one’s own level.</sentence>
			<sentence num="109">And however absurd, however unbelievable our whole conversation was, my heart shook.</sentence>
			<sentence num="110">Suddenly she burst out laughing. We were sitting on a bench then in front of the playing children, across from the place where carriages stopped and unloaded the public on the avenue before the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="111">“Do you see that fat baroness?” she cried. “It’s Baroness Wurmerhelm. She came only three days ago.</sentence>
			<sentence num="112">See her husband: a long, dry Prussian with a stick in his hand?</sentence>
			<sentence num="113">Remember him looking us over two days ago?</sentence>
			<sentence num="114">Go now, walk over to the baroness, take off your hat, and say something to her in French.” “Why?” “You swore you’d jump off the Schlangenberg; you swear you’re ready to kill if I order it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="115">Instead of all these killings and tragedies, I want only to laugh.</sentence>
			<sentence num="116">Go without any excuses. I want to see the baron beat you with his stick.” “You’re challenging me; you think I won’t do it?” “Yes, I’m challenging you, go, that’s how I want it!” “I’ll go, if you please, though it’s a wild fantasy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="117">Only here’s the thing: won’t there be trouble for the general, and for you through him?</sentence>
			<sentence num="118">By God, I don’t worry about myself, but about you, well–and the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="119">And what is this fantasy of going and insulting a woman?” “No, you’re a mere babbler, I can see,” she said contemptuously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="120">“Your eyes became bloodshot earlier–however, maybe that’s because you drank a lot of wine at dinner. As if I don’t understand myself that it’s stupid, and trite, and that the general will get angry?</sentence>
			<sentence num="121">I simply want to laugh. Well, I want to, that’s all!</sentence>
			<sentence num="122">And why should you insult a woman?</sentence>
			<sentence num="123">You’ll sooner get beaten with a stick.” I turned and silently went to do her bidding. Of course it was stupid, and of course I failed to get out of it, but as I went up to the baroness, I remember something seemed to egg me on, namely, schoolboy prankishness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="124">And I was terribly worked up, as if drunk.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="6" name="CHAPTER VI">
			<sentence num="1"> TWO DAYS HAVE NOW gone by since that stupid day.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">And so much shouting, noising, knocking, talking!</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">And it’s all such disorder, confusion, stupidity, and banality, and I’m the cause of it all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">However, sometimes it seems funny–to me at any rate.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">I’m unable to give myself an accounting for what has happened to me, whether I’m indeed in a state of frenzy, or have simply jumped off the rails and gone on a rampage till they tie me up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">At times it seems I’m going mad.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">And at times it seems I’m still not far from childhood, from the schoolbench, and it’s simply crude prankishness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">It’s Polina, it’s all Polina!</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">Maybe there would be no schoolboy pranks if it weren’t for her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">Who knows, maybe I’m doing it all out of despair (however stupid it is to reason this way).</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">And I don’t understand, I don’t understand what’s so good about her!</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">Goodlooking she is, though; yes, it seems she’s goodlooking.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Others lose their minds over her, too.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">She’s tall and trim.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Only very thin.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">It seems to me you could tie her in a knot or bend her double.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">The print of her foot is narrow and long–tormenting. Precisely tormenting.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">Her hair has a reddish tint.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">Her eyes–a real cat’s, but how proud and arrogant she can look with them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">Four months ago, when I had just entered their service, she had a long and heated conversation with des Grieux one evening in the drawing room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">And she looked at him in such a way… that later, when I went to my room to go to bed, I imagined that she had given him a slap–given it a moment before, then stood in front of him and looked at him… That evening I fell in love with her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">However, to business.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">I went down the path to the avenue, stood in the middle of the avenue, and waited for the baroness and baron.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">From five paces away I took off my hat and bowed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">I remember the baroness was wearing a silk dress of boundless circumference, light gray in color, with flounces, a crinoline, and a train.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">She was short and extraordinarily fat, with a terribly fat, pendulous chin, so that her neck couldn’t be seen at all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">A purple face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Small eyes, wicked and insolent.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">She walks along as if she’s doing everyone an honor.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">The baron is dry, tall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">His face, as German faces usually are, is crooked and covered with a thousand tiny wrinkles; eyeglasses; fortyfive years old.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">His legs begin almost at the level of his chest; that takes breeding. Proud as a peacock.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">A bit clumsy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">Something sheeplike in the expression of his face, which in its way replaces profundity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">All this flashed in my eyes within three seconds.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">My bow and the hat in my hand at first barely caught their attention.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">Only the baron knitted his brows slightly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">The baroness just came sailing towards me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">“ Then I bowed, put my hat on, and walked past the baron, politely turning my face to him and smiling. She had told me to take off my hat, but the bowing and prankishness were all my own. Devil knows what pushed me. It was as if I was flying off a hilltop.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">“ I turned and stopped in respectful expectation, continuing to look at him and smile.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">He was obviously perplexed and raised his eyebrows to the “ “ “ “ The baron and baroness quickly turned and all but fled from me in fright.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">Some of the public started talking, others looked at me in perplexity. However, I don’t remember it very well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">I turned and walked at an ordinary pace towards Polina Alexandrovna.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">But I was still about a hundred yards from her bench when I saw her get up and go towards the hotel with the children.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">I caught up with her by the porch.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“I performed… the foolery,” I said, drawing even with her. “Well, what of it? Now you can deal with it,” she replied, without even looking at me, and went up the stairs. That whole evening I spent walking in the park.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">Through the park and then through the woods, I even walked to another principality.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">{8} In one cottage I ate scrambled eggs and drank wine. For this idyll I was fleeced as much as one and a half thalers.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">I came home only at eleven o’clock.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">The general sent for me at once. Our people occupy two suites in the hotel; they have four rooms.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">The first–a big one–is the salon, with a grand piano. Next to it another big room–the general’s study.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">He was waiting for me there, standing in the middle of the study in an extemely majestic attitude.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">Des Grieux was sprawled on the sofa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">“My dear sir, allow me to ask, what you have done?” the general began, addressing me. “I would like you to get straight to the point, General,” I said.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">“You probably want to speak of my encounter with a certain German today?” “A certain German?!</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">This German is Baron Wurmerhelm and an important person, sir! You were rude to him and to the baroness.” “Not in the least.” “You frightened them, my dear sir,” cried the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">“Not at all. Back in Berlin this I confess, I was terribly glad of this highly schoolboyish explanation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">I had an astonishing wish to smear the whole story around as absurdly as possible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">And the further it went, the more I got a taste for it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">“Are you laughing at me, or what?” shouted the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">He turned to the Frenchman and told him in French that I was decidedly inviting a scandal.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">Des Grieux smiled contemptuously and shrugged his shoulders.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">“Oh, don’t think that, it’s nothing of the sort!” I cried to the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">“My act was not nice, of course, and I admit it to you frankly in the highest degree.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">My act may even be called stupid and indecent prankishness, but–nothing more.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">And you know, General, I’m repentant in the highest degree.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">But there’s one circumstance here which, in my eyes, almost even spares me any repentance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">Lately, for some two or even three weeks, I’ve been feeling unwell: sick, nervous, irritable, fantastic, and on some occasions I even lose all control of myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Really, I’ve sometimes wanted terribly to address the marquis des Grieux all at once and… However, there’s no point in saying it; he may get offended. In short, these are signs of illness. I don’t know whether Baroness Wurmerhelm will take that circumstance into consideration when I offer my apologies (because I intend to apologize).</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">I suppose she won’t, the less so in that, from what I know, this circumstance has lately been misused in the legal world: in criminal trials, lawyers have begun quite frequently to justify their clients, the criminals, by saying that at the moment of the crime they remembered nothing and that it was supposedly some such illness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">‘He beat someone,’ they say, ‘and remembers nothing.’ And imagine, General, medical science agrees with them–it really confirms that there is such an illness, such a temporary madness, when a man remembers almost nothing, or halfremembers, or a quarterremembers.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">But the baron and baroness are people of the older generation, and Prussian Junkers and landowners to boot.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">They must still be unfamiliar with this progress in the legal and medical world, and therefore will not accept my explanations.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">What do you think, General?” “Enough, sir!” the general uttered sharply and with restrained indignation, “enough!</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">I will try to rid myself once and for all of your prankishness. Apologize to the baron and baroness you will not.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">Any relations with you, even if they consist solely of your asking forgiveness, would be too humiliating for them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">The baron, having learned that you belong to my household, already had a talk with me in the vauxhall, and, I confess to you, a little more and he would have demanded satisfaction from me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">Do you realize what you have subjected me to–me, my dear sir? I, I was forced to offer my apologies to the baron and give him my word that, immediately, this very day, you would cease to belong to my household… ” “Pardon me, pardon me, General, so it was he himself who absolutely demanded that I not belong to your household, as you’re pleased to put it?” “No; but I myself considered it my duty to give him that satisfaction, and, naturally, the baron remained pleased.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">We are parting, my dear sir. I still owe you those four friedrichs d’or and three florins in local currency. Here’s the money, and here’s the paper with the accounting; you may verify it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">Goodbye. We are strangers from here on out.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">I have seen nothing from you but trouble and unpleasantness. I will summon the desk clerk at once and announce to him that starting tomorrow I do not answer for your hotel expenses.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">I have the honor to remain your obedient servant.” I took the money, the paper on which the accounting was penciled, bowed to the general, and said to him quite gravely: “General, the matter cannot end this way. I am very sorry that you were subjected to unpleasantness by the baron, but–excuse me–you yourself are to blame for it. How is it that you took it upon yourself to answer to the baron for me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">What is the meaning of the expression that I belong to your household?</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">I am simply a tutor in your house, and only that. I am not your son, I am not under your guardianship, and you cannot answer for my acts. I am a legally competent person. I am twentyfive years old, I have a university degree, I am a nobleman, I am a perfect stranger to you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">Only my boundless respect for your merits keeps me from demanding satisfaction from you right now and a further accounting for the fact that you took upon yourself the right to answer for me.” The general was so dumbfounded that he spread his arms, then turned to the Frenchman and told him hurriedly that I had just all but challenged him to a duel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">The Frenchman guffawed loudly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">“But I do not intend to let the baron off,” I continued with perfect equanimity, not embarrassed in the least by M. des Grieux’s laughter, “and since you, General, by consenting today to listen to the baron’s complaint, and thereby entering into his interests, have put yourself in the position of a participant, as it were, in this whole business, I have the honor to inform you that, no later than tomorrow morning, I will, in my own name, demand a formal explanation from the baron of the reasons why, having business with me, he bypassed me and addressed himself to another person, as if I could not or was not worthy to answer him for myself.” What I anticipated happened.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">The general, hearing this new silliness, became terribly scared.</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">“What, can you really intend to go on with this cursed business?” he cried. “But what are you doing to me, oh, Lord! Don’t you dare, don’t you dare, my dear sir, or I swear to you!… There are authorities here, too, and I… I… in short, by my rank… and the baron also… in short, you’ll be arrested and sent away from here by the police, so that you won’t make a row!</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">Understand that, sir!” And though he was choking with wrath, all the same he was terribly scared.</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">“General,” I replied, with an equanimity intolerable to him, “one cannot be arrested for rowdiness before there’s any rowdiness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">I have not yet begun my talk with the baron, and it is as yet completely unknown to you in what manner and on what basis I intend to go about the business.</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">My only wish is to clarify the offensive suggestion that I am under the guardianship of a person who supposedly has power over my free will.</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">You needn’t trouble and worry yourself so much.” “For God’s sake, for God’s sake, Alexei Ivanovich, drop this senseless intention!” the general muttered, suddenly changing his wrathful tone to a pleading one and even seizing me by the hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">“Well, imagine what will come of it? Another unpleasantness! You must agree, I have to behave myself in a special manner here, especially now!… especially now!… Oh, you don’t know, you don’t know all my circumstances!… When we leave here, I’m prepared to take you back.</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">It’s only just so, well, in short–you do understand the reasons!” he cried desperately.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">“Alexei Ivanovich, Alexei Ivanovich!… ” Retreating to the door, I again earnestly begged him not to worry, promised that everything would turn out well and decently, and hastened to leave.</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">Russians abroad are sometimes much too cowardly and are terribly afraid of what will be said of them, and how they’ll be looked at, and whether this or that will be proper; in short, they behave as if they’re in corsets, especially those who make claims to significance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">What they like most is some preconceived, preestablished form, which they follow slavishly–in hotels, on promenades, at assemblies, while traveling… But on top of that the general had let slip that he had some special circumstances, that he somehow had to “behave specially.” That was why he was suddenly so pusillanimous and cowardly and changed his tone with me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">I took that into consideration and made note of it. And, of course, tomorrow he might foolishly turn to some authorities, so that I indeed had to be careful. However, I had no interest at all in angering the general himself; but I did want to anger Polina a little now. Polina had dealt so cruelly with me, and had pushed me onto such a stupid path, that I wanted very much to drive her to the point of asking me to stop.</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">My prankishness might finally compromise her as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">Besides that, some other sensations and desires were taking shape in me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">If, for instance, I voluntarily vanish into nothing before her, that does not at all mean that I’m a wet chicken before people, and it is certainly not for the baron to “beat me with a stick.” I wanted to make fun of them all and come out as a fine fellow.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">Let them see. Never fear! she’ll be afraid of a scandal and call for me again. And if she doesn’t, she’ll still see that I’m not a wet chicken… (Astonishing news: I’ve just heard from our nanny, whom I met on the stairs, that Marya Filippovna set off today for Karlsbad, all by herself, on the evening train, to visit her cousin.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">What kind of news is that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">The nanny says she had been intending to for a long time; but how is it no one knew?</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">However, maybe only I didn’t know. The nanny let slip that Marya Filippovna had had a big talk with the general two days ago. I understand, sir. It’s probably–Mlle Blanche.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">Yes, something decisive is coming for us.)</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="7" name="CHAPTER VII">
			<sentence num="1"> THE NEXT MORNING I sent for the desk clerk and told him that my account should be kept separately.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">My room was not so expensive that I should get very frightened and leave the hotel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">I had sixteen friedrichs d’or, and there… there, maybe, lay riches!</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">Strange thing, I haven’t won yet, but I act, feel, and think like a rich man, and I can’t imagine myself otherwise.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">I planned, despite the early hour, to go at once and see Mr. Astley at the Hôtel d’Angleterre, very near us, when suddenly des Grieux came into my room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">This had never happened before, and, on top of that, the gentleman and I had lately been in the most alienated and strained relations.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">He plainly did not conceal his contempt for me, even made an effort not to conceal it; while I–I had my own reasons not to favor him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">In short, I hated him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">His visit surprised me very much.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">I realized at once that something very special was brewing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">He came in very amiably and paid my room a compliment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">Seeing that I had my hat in my hand, he inquired if I was really going for a walk so early.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">When he heard that I was going to see Mr. Astley on business, he reflected, understood, and his face acquired an extremely preoccupied look.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">Des Grieux was like all Frenchmen, that is, cheerful and amiable when it was necessary and profitable, and insufferably dull when the necessity to be cheerful and amiable ceased.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">A Frenchman is rarely amiable by nature; he is always amiable as if on command, out of calculation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">If, for instance, he sees the necessity of being fantastic, original, out of the ordinary, then his fantasy, being most stupid and unnatural, assembles itself out of “I’ve come to see you on business,” he began extremely independently, though, by the way, politely, “and I will not conceal that I’ve come as an ambassador or, better to say, a mediator from the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">Knowing Russian very poorly, I understood almost nothing yesterday; but the general explained it to me in detail, and I confess… ” “Listen, M. des Grieux,” I interrupted him, “here you’ve undertaken to be a mediator in this business as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">I am, of course, ‘ He didn’t like my question. It was only too transparent for him, and he didn’t want to let anything slip. “I am connected with the general partly by business, partly by I objected to him quite calmly that he was somewhat mistaken; that maybe I would not be chased out of the baron’s, but, on the contrary, be listened to; and I asked him to admit that he had probably come in order to worm out of me precisely how I was going to set about this whole business.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">“Oh, God, since the general is so involved, he would certainly like to know what you are going to do and how!</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">It’s so natural!” I started to explain, and he began to listen, sprawling, cocking his head slightly towards me, with an obvious, unconcealed ironic nuance in his face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">In general, he behaved with extreme haughtiness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">I tried with all my might to pretend that I looked at the business from the most serious point of view. I explained that, since the baron had addressed a complaint against me to the general, as though I was the general’s servant, he had, first of all, deprived me thereby of my post, and, second, treated me as a person who is unable to answer for himself and is not worth talking to.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">Of course, I am justified in feeling myself offended; however, understanding the difference in age, of position in society, and so on, and so forth (I could barely keep from laughing at this point), I do not want to take another frivolity upon myself, that is, directly demand satisfaction from the baron, or even merely suggest it to him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">Nevertheless, I consider myself perfectly within my rights in offering him, and especially the baroness, my apologies, the more so in that lately I have indeed been feeling unwell, upset, and, so to speak, fantastic, and so on, and so forth.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">However, by offensively addressing the general yesterday and insisting that the general deprive me of my post, the baron has put me in such a position that I can no longer offer him and the baroness my apologies, because he, and the baroness, and the whole world would probably think I am coming with my apologies out of fear, in order to get my post back.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">It follows from all this that I now find myself forced to ask the baron to apologize to me first, in the most moderate terms–for instance, by saying he had by no means wished to offend me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">And once the baron speaks it out, then I, my hands now untied, will offer him my openhearted and sincere apologies. In short, I concluded, I ask only that the baron untie my hands. “Fie, such scrupulousness and such subtleties! And why should you apologize?</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Well, you will agree, “Excuse me, “ “And what is it to the general? He said something yesterday about having to keep himself on some sort of footing… and he was so alarmed… but I understood nothing.” “Here there is… here precisely there exists a special circumstance,” des Grieux picked up in a pleading tone, in which more and more vexation could be heard.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">“Do you know Mlle de Cominges?” “You mean Mlle Blanche?” “Well, yes, Mlle Blanche de Cominges… “I don’t see any scandals or stories here that have anything to do with his marriage.” “But “It will be with me, then, not with you, since I no longer belong to the household… ” (I deliberately tried to be as muddleheaded as possible.) “But, excuse me, so it’s decided that Mlle Blanche will marry the general?</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">What are they waiting for? I mean to say–why conceal it, at any rate from us, the household?” “I cannot tell you… however, it is still not entirely… though… you know, they are waiting for news from Russia; the general must arrange his affairs… ” “Aha!</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">Des Grieux looked at me with hatred. “In short,” he interrupted, “I fully trust in your innate courtesy, your intelligence, your tact… you will, of course, do it for the family, in which you were like their own, were loved, respected… ” “Good God, I’ve been thrown out!</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">You insist now that it was for the sake of appearances; but you must agree that if you say: ‘Of course, I don’t want to box your ears, but for the sake of appearances allow me to box your ears… ’ Well, isn’t it almost the same?” “If so, if no entreaties have any influence on you,” he began sternly and presumptuously, “then allow me to assure you that measures will be taken.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">There are authorities here, you will be sent away today– “But I won’t go myself,” I replied with extraordinary calm, “you’re mistaken, M. des Grieux, it will all work out with much greater decency than you think.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">I will now go to Mr. Astley and ask him to be my mediator, in short, to be my second. The man likes me and certainly will not refuse me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">He will go to the baron, and the baron will receive him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">If I myself am The Frenchman was decidedly scared; indeed, it all very much resembled the truth, and consequently it appeared that I really was capable of starting a whole story.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">“But I beg you,” he began in a thoroughly pleading voice, “drop it all! It is as if you are pleased that a whole story will come of it!</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">It is not satisfaction you want, but a story! I told you, it will come out amusing and even clever–which is maybe what you are after–but, in short,” he concluded, seeing that I had stood up and was taking my hat, “I have come to convey to you these few words from a certain person.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">Read them. I was told to wait for an answer.” So saying, he took from his pocket a little note, folded and sealed with wax, and handed it to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">It was written in Polina’s hand: Everything seemed to turn upside down as I read these lines.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">My lips went white, and I began to tremble. The cursed Frenchman looked on with an exaggeratedly modest air and averted his eyes from me, as if in order not to see my confusion.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">It would have been better if he had burst out laughing at me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“Very well,” I said, “tell “Oh, I wanted… generally this is all so strange that you must pardon my natural impatience. I wanted the sooner to learn your intentions for myself, from you personally.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">However, I do not know what is in this note, and thought I would always have time to give it to you.” “I see, you were simply told to give it to me as a last resort, and not to give it if you could settle it verbally.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">Right? Talk straight, M. des Grieux!” “ I took my hat; he inclined his head and left. I fancied there was a mocking smile on his lips. And how could it be otherwise?</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“We’ll settle accounts, Frenchy, we’ll measure forces!” I muttered, going down the stairs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">I still couldn’t grasp anything, as if I’d been hit on the head. The fresh air revived me a little. After a couple of minutes, when I just began to grasp things clearly, two thoughts distinctly presented themselves to me:</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="8" name="CHAPTER VIII">
			<sentence num="1"> ON THE PROMENADE, as they call it here, that is, the chestnut avenue, I met my Englishman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">“Oho!” he began when he saw me, “I’m going to you, and you to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">So you’ve already parted from your people?” “Tell me, first of all, how you know about all this,” I asked in surprise.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">“Can it be that everybody knows all about it?” “Oh, no, everybody does not know; and it’s better if they don’t.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">Nobody’s talking about it.” “Then how do you know?” “I know because I chanced to learn.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">Now where are you going to go from here? I like you, that’s why I was coming to see you.” “You’re a nice man, Mr. Astley,” I said (though I was terribly struck: where did he find out?</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">), “and since I haven’t had my coffee yet, and you probably did a poor job on yours, let’s go to the vauxhall café, sit there, have a smoke, and I’ll tell you everything, and… you’ll also tell me.” The café was a hundred paces away.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">Coffee was brought, we sat down, I lit a cigarette, Mr. Astley didn’t light anything and, fixing his eyes on me, prepared to listen.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">“I’m not going to go anywhere, I’m staying here,” I began.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">“I was just sure you’d stay,” Mr. Astley said approvingly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">On my way to see Mr. Astley, I had had no intention and even purposely did not want to tell him anything about my love for Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">In all those days I had scarcely said a single word to him about it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Besides, he was very shy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">I had noticed from the first that Polina had made a great impression on him, but he never mentioned her name.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">But, strangely, suddenly, now, as soon as he sat down and fixed me with his intent, tinny gaze, an urge came over me, I don’t know why, to tell him everything, that is, all my love and with all its nuances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">I spent a whole halfhour telling him, and I found it extremely pleasant to be telling about it for the first time!</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">Noticing that in some especially ardent places he became embarrassed, I deliberately increased the ardor of my story.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">One thing I regret: I may have said some unnecessary things about the Frenchman… Mr. Astley listened, sitting opposite me, without moving, without uttering a word or a sound, and looking me in the eye; but when I started speaking of the Frenchman, he suddenly cut me short and asked sternly whether I had the right to mention this extraneous circumstance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">Mr. Astley always put his questions in a very strange way.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">“You’re right: I’m afraid I don’t,” I replied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">“You can say nothing precise about this marquis and Miss Polina, apart from mere surmises?” Again I was surprised at such a categorical question from such a shy man as Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">“No, nothing precise,” I replied, “of course not.” “If so, you have done a wrong thing not only in talking about it with me, but even in thinking about it to yourself.” “All right, all right!</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">I acknowledge it; but that’s not the point now,” I interrupted, surprised in myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">Here I told him the whole of yesterday’s story in all its details, Polina’s escapade, my adventure with the baron, my dismissal, the general’s extraordinary cowardice, and finally I gave him a detailed account of today’s visit from des Grieux, with all its nuances; in conclusion, I showed him the note.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">“What do you make of it?” I asked.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">“I was precisely coming to learn your thoughts.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">As for me, I think I could kill that little Frenchman, and maybe I will.” “And I, too,” said Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">“As for Miss Polina… you know, we enter into relations even with people we hate, if necessity demands it of us.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">Here there may be relations unknown to you, which depend on extraneous circumstances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">I think you can rest easy–in part, to be sure.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">As for her action yesterday, it is, of course, strange–not because she wanted to get rid of you and sent you under the baron’s stick (which he didn’t use, though I don’t understand why, since he had it in his hand), but because such an escapade from such a… from such an excellent miss… is improper.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Naturally, she couldn’t have foreseen that you would literally carry out her jesting wish… ” “You know what?” I cried suddenly, peering intently at Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">“I have the feeling that you’ve already heard about all this, and do you know from whom?–from Miss Polina herself!” Mr. Astley looked at me in surprise.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">“Your eyes flash, and I read suspicion in them,” he said, recovering his former equanimity at once, “but you haven’t the least right to reveal your suspicions.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">I cannot acknowledge that right, and I totally refuse to answer your question.” “Well, enough!</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">And you needn’t!” I cried, strangely agitated and not understanding why that had popped into my mind!</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">And when, where, how could Mr. Astley have been chosen by Polina as a confidant?</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">Lately, however, I had partially let Mr. Astley slip from sight, and Polina had always been an enigma to me–so much an enigma that now, for instance, in setting out to tell Mr. Astley the whole history of my love, I was suddenly struck, during the telling, by the fact that I could say almost nothing precise and positive about my relations with her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">On the contrary, everything was fantastic, strange, insubstantial, and even bore no resemblance to anything.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">“Well, all right, all right; I’m confused, and now there are still many things I can’t grasp,” I replied as if breathlessly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">“However, you’re a good man.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">Now it’s a different matter, and I ask your–not advice, but opinion.” I paused and began: “Why do you think the general got so scared?</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">Why did they make such a story out of my most stupid mischievousness?</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">Such a story that even des Grieux himself found it necessary to interfere (and he interferes only in the most important cases), visited me (how about that!</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">), begged, pleaded with me–he, des Grieux, with me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">Finally, note for yourself that he came at nine o’clock, just before nine, and Miss Polina’s note was already in his hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">When, may I ask, was it written?</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">Maybe Miss Polina was awakened just for that!</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">Besides, from that I can see that Miss Polina is his slave (because she even asked my forgiveness!</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">)–besides that, what is all this to her, to her personally?</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">Why is she so interested?</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">Why are they afraid of some baron?</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">And so what if the general is marrying Mlle Blanche de Cominges?</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">They say they have to behave in some Mr. Astley smiled and nodded his head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">“Indeed, it seems that in this, too, I know a great deal more than you do,” he said.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">“This whole business concerns Mlle Blanche alone, and I’m sure it’s perfectly true.” “Well, what about Mlle Blanche?” I cried impatiently (I suddenly had a hope that something would be revealed now about Mlle Polina).</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">“It seems to me that Mlle Blanche has at the present moment a special interest in avoiding any kind of meeting with the baron and baroness–all the more so an unpleasant meeting, worse still a scandalous one.” “Well?</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">Well?” “Two years ago, Mlle Blanche was here in Roulettenburg during the season.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">And I also happened to be here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">Mlle Blanche was not known as Mlle de Cominges then, nor was her mother, Madame “But he does have a respectable circle of acquaintances?” “Oh, that may be.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">Even Mlle Blanche may.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">But two years ago Mlle Blanche, on a complaint from this same baroness, received an invitation from the local police to leave town, and leave she did.” “How was that?” “She appeared here first then with an Italian, some sort of prince with a historic name something like “Oh, yes.” “They’re not worth noticing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">To the vexation of the decent public, there’s no lack of them here, at any rate those of them who change thousandfranc notes at the tables every day.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">However, as soon as they stop changing notes, they’re immediately asked to leave. Mlle Zelmà still went on changing notes; but her game went still more unluckily.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Note that these ladies are quite often lucky at gambling; they have astonishing selfcontrol.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">However, my story is over. One day, exactly like the prince, the count, too, vanished.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">Mlle Zelmà appeared in the evening to play alone; this time no one appeared to offer her his arm.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">In two days she lost everything.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Having staked her last louis d’or and lost it, she looked around and saw Baron Wurmerhelm nearby, studying her with great attention and deep indignation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">But Mlle Zelmà did not perceive the indignation and, turning to the baron with a certain kind of smile, asked him to put ten louis d’or on red for her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">As a result of that, on the baroness’s complaint, she received that evening an invitation not to appear in the vauxhall anymore.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">If it surprises you that I know all these small and completely indecent details, it is because I finally heard them from Mr. Feeder, a relation of mine, who that same evening took Mlle Zelmà in his carriage from Roulettenburg to Spa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">Now understand: Mlle Blanche wants to become the general’s wife, probably, so that she will never again receive such invitations as she did two years ago from the vauxhall police.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">Now she no longer gambles; but that is because, by all tokens, she now has capital, which she lends to local gamblers on interest. That is much more prudent.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">I even suspect that the unfortunate general owes her money. Maybe des Grieux does, too. Maybe des Grieux is her associate.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">You must agree that, at least until the wedding, she would not wish to attract the attention of the baron or the baroness for any reason. In short, in her position scandal is the least profitable thing for her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">You are connected with their household, and your acts could cause a scandal, the more so as she appears every day in public arm in arm with the general or with Miss Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">Now do you understand?” “No, I don’t!” I cried, banging the table with all my might, so that the frightened “Tell me, Mr. Astley,” I repeated in frenzy, “if you know this whole story, and consequently know by heart what Mlle Blanche de Cominges is–how is it that you haven’t warned at least me, the general himself, and above all Miss Polina, who has appeared here in the vauxhall, in public, arm in arm with Mlle Blanche?</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">Can this be possible?” “There was no point in warning you, because there was nothing you could do,” Mr. Astley replied calmly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">“And anyhow, what was there to warn you about?</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">The general may know more about Mlle Blanche than I do, and all the same he goes strolling with her and Miss Polina. The general is an unfortunate man.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">Yesterday I saw Mlle Blanche riding a splendid horse with M. des Grieux and that little Russian prince, and the general riding behind them on a chestnut.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">In the morning he had said that his legs hurt, but he sat his horse well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">And at that moment the thought suddenly occurred to me that this was a completely lost man.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">Moreover, this is all none of my business, and I had the honor of meeting Miss Polina only recently.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">However,” Mr. Astley suddenly caught himself, “I’ve already told you that I cannot acknowledge your right to certain questions, though I sincerely like you… ” “Enough,” I said, getting up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">“It’s clear as day to me now that Miss Polina also knows all about Mlle Blanche, but she can’t part with her Frenchman, and therefore ventures to stroll with Mlle Blanche.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">Believe me, no other influence would induce her to stroll with Mlle Blanche and beg me in a note not to touch the baron. Here there must be precisely that influence before which everything bows! And yet it was she who loosed me on the baron! Devil take it, nothing can be sorted out here!” “You forget, first, that this Mlle de Cominges is the general’s fiancée, and, second, that Miss Polina, the general’s stepdaughter, has a little brother and sister, the general’s own children, totally abandoned by this crazy man and, it seems, robbed as well.” “Yes, yes, that’s so!</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">Leaving the children means abandoning them completely, staying means protecting their interests, and maybe saving shreds of the estate as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">Yes, yes, that’s all true! But still, still!</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">Oh, I understand why they’re all now so interested in “In whom?” asked Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">“In that old witch in Moscow who won’t die and about whom they’re expecting a telegram that she’s dead.” “Well, yes, of course, the whole interest converges in her. The whole point lies in the inheritance!</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">When the inheritance is announced, the general will get married; Miss Polina will be unbound, and des Grieux… ” “Well, and des Grieux?” “Des Grieux will be paid his money; that’s all he’s waiting for here.” “All!</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">You think that’s all he’s waiting for?” “I know nothing more.” Mr. Astley fell stubbornly silent.</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">“But I know, I know!” I repeated in a rage.</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">“He’s also waiting for the inheritance, because Polina will get a dowry, and once she gets the money, she’ll immediately throw herself on his neck.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">Women are all like that!</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">And the proudest of them come out as the most banal slaves! Polina is capable only of loving passionately and nothing more!</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">That’s my opinion of her! Look at her, especially when she’s sitting alone, deep in thought: it’s something predestined, foredoomed, accursed!</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">She’s capable of all the horrors of life and passion… she… she… but who’s that calling me?” I suddenly exclaimed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">“Who’s shouting?</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">I heard somebody shout ‘Alexei Ivanovich!’ in Russian. A woman’s voice, listen, listen!” At that moment we were approaching our hotel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">We had left the café long ago, almost without noticing it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">“I heard a woman shout, but I don’t know who she’s calling; it was in Russian.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">Now I can see where it’s coming from,” Mr. Astley was pointing, “it’s that woman shouting, the one sitting in a big armchair and who has just been carried up to the porch by so many footmen.</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">They’re carrying her suitcases behind her; that means the train has just arrived.” “But why is she calling me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">She’s shouting again; look, she’s waving to us.” “I see that she’s waving,” said Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">“Alexei Ivanovich! Alexei Ivanovich! Ah, Lord, what a dolt!” desperate cries came from the porch of the hotel. We almost ran to the entrance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="109">I reached the landing and… my arms dropped in amazement, and my feet became rooted to the stone.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="9" name="CHAPTER IX">
			<sentence num="1"> ON THE UPPER LANDING of the wide hotel porch, carried up the steps in a chair and surrounded by manservants and maidservants and the numerous, obsequious hotel staff, in the presence of the manager himself, who had come out to meet the exalted guest arriving with so much flurry and noise, with her own servants and with so many suitcases and valises, sat– “Well, what are you doing, dearie, standing in front of me with your eyes popping out!” grandmother went on yelling at me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">“You don’t know how to bow and greet a body, eh? Or you’ve grown proud and don’t want to? Or maybe you don’t recognize me? You hear, Potapych,” she turned to a grayhaired old man in a tailcoat and white tie and with a pink bald spot, her butler, who had accompanied her on her journey, “you hear, he doesn’t recognize me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">They’ve got me buried! They send one telegram after another: is she dead or not? I know everything! And here, you see, I’m as alive as can be!” “Good heavens, Antonida Vassilyevna, why would I wish you ill?” I answered cheerfully, coming to my senses.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">“I was only surprised… And how not marvel at such an unexpected… ” “But what’s so surprising for you?</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">I got on the train and came. It’s a quiet ride, no jolts. You’ve been for a walk, have you?” “Yes, I strolled to the vauxhall.” “It’s nice here,” said grandmother, looking around, “warm, and there’s a wealth of trees. I like that.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">Are our people at home? The general?” “Oh, yes! at this hour they’re probably all at home.” “So they’ve established a schedule here and all the ceremonies? Setting the tone.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">I’ve heard they keep a carriage, “Yes, Polina Alexandrovna, too.” “And the little Frenchman?</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">Well, I’ll see them all for myself, Alexei Ivanovich, show me the way straight to him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">Do you find it nice here?” “So so, Antonida Vassilyevna.” “And you, Potapych, tell that dolt of a manager to give me comfortable quarters, nice ones, not too high up, and carry my things there at once.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">Why is everybody in a rush to carry me? Why are they getting at me? Eh, what slaves! Who’s that with you?” she turned to me again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">“This is Mr. Astley,” I replied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">“Who is this Mr. Astley?” “A traveler, my good acquaintance; he also knows the general.” “An Englishman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">That’s why he’s staring at me and doesn’t unclench his teeth.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">I like Englishmen, though. Well, drag me upstairs, straight to their place; where are they?” Grandmother was carried; I walked ahead up the wide hotel stairway.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Our procession was very impressive. Everyone who came our way stopped and looked at us all eyes. Our hotel was considered the best, the most expensive, and the most aristocratic at the spa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">On the stairs and in the corridors one always met magnificent ladies and important Englishmen.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">Many made inquiries downstairs of the manager, who, for his own part, was deeply impressed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">He, of course, replied to all who asked that this was an important foreign lady, “She interests me greatly,” Mr. Astley whispered to me, going up the stairs beside me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">“She knows about the telegrams,” I thought, “she’s also been informed about des Grieux, but it seems she still knows little about Mlle Blanche.” I immediately communicated this to Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">Sinful man! My first surprise had no sooner passed, than I rejoiced terribly at the thunderbolt we were about to produce at the general’s.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">It was as if something was egging me on, and I led the way extremely cheerfully.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">Our people were quartered on the second floor.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">I made no announcement, did not even knock at the door, but simply thrust it open, and grandmother was carried in in triumph.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">As if on purpose, they were all gathered in the general’s study. It was twelve o’clock, and they seemed to be planning an excursion–some were going in carriages, others on horseback, the entire company; besides that, other acquaintances had been invited.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">Besides the general, Polina with the children, their nanny, there were in the study: des Grieux, Mlle Blanche, again in a riding habit, her mother Mme “Well, here I am!</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">Instead of a telegram!” grandmother burst out at last, breaking the silence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">“What, you didn’t expect me?” “Antonida Vassilyevna… auntie… but how on earth… ” the unfortunate general murmured.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">If grandmother hadn’t begun speaking for a few seconds more, he might have had a stroke.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">“What do you mean, how? I got on the train and came.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">What’s the railroad for? And you all thought I’d stretched out my bones and left you an inheritance?</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">I know how you sent telegrams from here. Paid a lot of money for them, I suppose.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">It’s not cheap from here. But I shouldered my old bones and came here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">Is this that Frenchman? M. des Grieux, I believe?” “ “Hm, “This is Mlle Blanche de Cominges, and this is her mother, Mme de Cominges; they’re staying at this hotel,” I reported.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">“Is the daughter married?” grandmother inquired without ceremony. “Mlle de Cominges is unmarried,” I replied as respectfully as I could, purposely lowering my voice.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">“A merry girl?” I didn’t understand the question at first. “She’s not boring to be with? Does she understand Russian?</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">This des Grieux picked up a smattering of it with us in Moscow.” I explained to her that Mlle de Cominges had never been to Russia.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">“ “ “Ah, she’s lowered her eyes, she’s mincing and prancing; you can tell the bird at once; some sort of actress. I’m staying downstairs in this hotel,” she suddenly turned to the general, “I shall be your neighbor; are you glad or not?” “Oh, auntie!</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">Believe in the sincere feeling… of my pleasure,” the general picked up. He had already recovered somewhat, and since he was capable on occasion of speaking aptly, imposingly, and with a claim to a certain effect, he began expatiating now as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">“We were so alarmed and struck by the news of your ill health… We received such hopeless telegrams, and suddenly… ” “Lies, lies!” grandmother interrupted at once.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">“But how is it,” the general also hastened to interrupt and raised his voice, trying to ignore this “lies,” “how is it, though, that you ventured upon such a journey?</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">You must agree that at your age and with your health… at any rate it’s all so unexpected that our astonishment is comprehensible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">But I’m so glad… and we all”(he started smiling sweetly and rapturously) “will try as hard as we can to make your season here pass most pleasantly… ” “Well, enough empty chatter; laying it on thick as usual; I can get along by myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">However, I have nothing against you; I don’t bear any grudges. How, you ask? What’s so surprising? In the simplest way.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">Why are they all so surprised? Hello, Praskovya.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">What are you doing here?” “Hello, grandmother,” said Polina, going up to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“Was it a long trip?” “Well, this one has asked the smartest question, none of this oh and ah! You see, I lay and lay, got treated and treated, then I chased the doctors away and summoned the sacristan from St. Nicholas’s.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">He had cured one woman of the same illness with hay dust.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">Well, and he helped me; on the third day I sweated all over and got up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">Then all my Germans gathered again, put on their spectacles, and began to opinionate: ‘If you were to go abroad now to a spa and take a cure,’ they said, ‘your gripes would go away completely.’ And why not?</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">I thought. The FoolBlazers start their ohing: ‘You can’t go so far!’ they say. Well, so there!</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">In one day I got ready and on Friday last week I took my maid, and Potapych, and the footman Fyodor, only in Berlin I chased this Fyodor home, because I saw there was simply no need for him, I could get here all by myself… I’m riding in a separate compartment, and there are porters at all the stations, they’ll carry me wherever I like for twenty kopecks.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">Look, what quarters you occupy!” she concluded, glancing around.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">“With what money are you paying for it, dearie? Everything you’ve got is mortgaged. You owe quite a lump to this little Frenchman alone! I know everything, everything!” “Auntie… ” the general began, all embarrassed, “I’m astonished, auntie… it seems that, even without anyone’s control, I can… what’s more, my expenses do not exceed my means, and here we… ” “Don’t exceed your means?</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">Come now! You must have robbed the children of their last penny–a fine guardian!” “After this, after such words… ” the general began indignantly, “I really don’t know… ” “He doesn’t know!</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">I’ll bet you never leave the roulette tables here!</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Have you blown it all?” The general was so astounded that he almost spluttered from the rush of his agitated feelings.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">“Roulette! I? With my importance… I? You forget yourself, auntie, you must still be unwell… ” “Lies, lies; I’ll bet they can’t drag you away; it’s all lies!</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">I’m going to have a look at what this roulette is right today.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">You, Praskovya, tell me what there is to be seen here, and Alexei Ivanovich will show me, and you, Potapych, write down all the places to go.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">What’s there to see here?” she suddenly turned to Polina again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">“There are the ruins of a castle nearby, then there’s the Schlangenberg.” “What is this Schlangenberg?</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">A woods, or what?” “No, not a woods, it’s a mountain; there’s a “What sort of “The highest part of the mountain, an enclosed place.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">The view from there is magnificent.” “That means dragging the armchair up the mountain.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Can it be done, or not?” “Oh, it should be possible to find porters,” I replied. At that moment, Fedosya, the nanny, came up to greet grandmother, bringing the general’s children. “Well, there’s no need for smooching! I don’t like to kiss children, they’re all snotty!</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">How are you getting on here, Fedosya?” “It’s vurry, vurry nice here, Antonida Vassilyevna, ma’am,” Fedosya replied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">“And how have you been, ma’am? We’ve been grieving over you so.” “I know, you’re a simple soul. What have you got here, all guests, or something?” she turned to Polina again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">“This runty one in the spectacles?” “That’s Prince Nilsky, grandmother,” Polina whispered to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">“A Russian? And I thought he wouldn’t understand! Maybe he didn’t hear! I’ve already seen Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Here he is again,” grandmother caught sight of him again. “Hello!” she suddenly addressed him. Mr. Astley silently bowed to her. “Well, do you have something nice to say to me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">Say something! Translate for him, Polina.” Polina translated.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">“That I am looking at you with great pleasure and rejoicing that you are in good health,” Mr. Astley replied gravely, but with great readiness. It was translated for grandmother, and she obviously liked it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">“Englishmen always answer well,” she observed. “For some reason I’ve always liked Englishmen, no comparison with these little Frenchmen! Call on me,” she turned to Mr. Astley again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">“I’ll try not to bother you too much. Translate it for him and tell him that I’m downstairs here, downstairs here–you hear, downstairs, downstairs,” she repeated to Mr. Astley, pointing down with her finger. Mr. Astley was extremely pleased with the invitation. Grandmother looked Polina over from head to foot with an attentive and satisfied gaze.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">“I could love you, Praskovya,” she said suddenly, “you’re a nice girl, better than all of them, but what a little character you’ve got–oof!</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">Well, yes, I have my character, too; turn around; that’s not a hairpiece, is it?” “No, grandmother, it’s my own.” “Hm, I don’t like this stupid modern fashion.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">You’re a very pretty girl. I’d fall in love with you if I were a young man. How is it you don’t get married?</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">However, it’s time I was off. I want to go outside, it’s been nothing but the train, the train… Well, what’s with you, still angry?” she turned to the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">“Come now, auntie, for pity’s sake!” the happy general roused himself. “I understand, at your age… ” “ “I want to have a look at everything here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">Will you lend me Alexei Ivanovich?” grandmother continued to the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">“Oh, for as long as you like, but I myself… and Polina, and M. des Grieux… we’ll all consider it a pleasure to accompany you… ” “ “Hm, Grandmother was lifted up again, and the whole crowd of us set out, following the armchair down the stairs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">The general walked as if stunned by the blow of a bludgeon on the head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">Des Grieux was mulling something over.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">Mlle Blanche made as if to stay, but then for some reason decided to go with everybody else. The prince at once set out after her, and only the German and Mme</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="10" name="CHAPTER X">
			<sentence num="1"> AT SPAS–AND, IT SEEMS, all over Europe–hotel administrators and managers, when assigning rooms to their guests, are guided not so much by their demands and wishes as by their own personal view of them; and, it must be noted, they are rarely mistaken.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">But grandmother, God knows why, was given such rich quarters that they even overdid it: four magnificently decorated rooms, with a bathroom, servants’ quarters, a special room for the maid, and so on, and so forth.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">Indeed, a week earlier some I don’t know who they took grandmother for, but it seems they thought her an extremely important and, above all, a very rich personage.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">They at once entered in the register: “ “Whose portrait is that?” The manager declared that it was probably some countess.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">“How is it you don’t know? You live here and you don’t know? What’s it doing here?</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">Why is she crosseyed?” The manager was unable to give satisfactory answers to all these questions and was even at a loss.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">“What a blockhead!” grandmother retorted in Russian. They carried her further on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">The same story was repeated with a Saxony statuette, which grandmother inspected for a long time and then ordered to be removed, no one knew why.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">She finally badgered the manager about the cost of the bedroom carpets and where they had been made.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">The manager promised to find out.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">“What asses!” grandmother grumbled and turned all her attention to the bed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">“Such a magnificent canopy! Unmake it.” The bed was unmade.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">“Go on, go on, unmake it all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">Take away the pillows, the pillowcases, lift up the feather bed.” Everything was turned upside down.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Remake it with my linen and my pillows.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">Anyhow, it’s all much too magnificent, an old woman like me doesn’t need such a suite: I’ll be bored by myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">Alexei Ivanovich, come and see me often, when you’re done teaching the children.” “Since yesterday I no longer work for the general,” I replied, “and I’m living in the hotel completely on my own.” “Why’s that?” “The other day a distinguished German baron and the baroness, his wife, came here from Berlin.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">Yesterday on the promenade I addressed him in German without keeping to the Berlin accent.” “Well, what of it?” “He considered it insolent and complained to the general, and the general dismissed me the same day.” “What, did you abuse him, this baron, or something?</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">(Even if you did, it wouldn’t matter!</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">)” “Oh, no. On the contrary, the baron raised his stick at me.” “And you, you dribbler, allowed your tutor to be treated that way,” she suddenly turned on the general, “and dismissed him from his post to boot!</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">You’re dunderheads–you’re all dunderheads, I can see.” “Don’t worry, auntie,” the general replied with a slight tinge of haughty familiarity, “I know how to handle my own affairs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">Besides, Alexei Ivanovich did not report it to you quite accurately.” “And you just let it pass?” she turned to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">“I wanted to challenge the baron to a duel,” I replied as modestly and calmly as I could, “but the general was against it.” “Why were you against it?” grandmother turned to the general again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">“(And you may go, dearie, come back when you’re called,” she also turned to the manager, “no point in standing there gaping.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">I can’t stand his Nuremberg mug!</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">)” The man bowed and left, without, of course, understanding grandmother’s compliment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">“Good heavens, auntie, duels really aren’t possible,” the general answered with a smile.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Men are all cocks, so they ought to fight.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">You’re all dunderheads. I can see, you don’t know how to stand up for your country.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">Well, lift me up!</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">Potapych, arrange it so that two porters are always ready, hire them and settle it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">No need for more than two.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">They’ll only have to carry me on the stairs, but on the level, on the street, they can roll me–tell them that; and pay them in advance, they’ll be more respectful.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">You yourself must always be with me, and you, Alexei Ivanovich, show me this baron on the promenade: I’d at least like to see what sort of von baron he is.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">Well, so where’s this roulette?” I explained that the roulette tables were in rooms of the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">Then followed questions: how many are there?</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">do many people play?</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">Does it go on all day?</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">How is it set up?</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">I answered, finally, that it would be best of all to see it with her own eyes, and that it was quite difficult to describe it just like that.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">“Well, then carry me straight there!</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">Lead the way, Alexei Ivanovich!” “Why, auntie, are you not even going to rest after the trip?” the general asked solicitously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">He seemed to be in a bit of a flutter, and they were all somehow perplexed and began exchanging glances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">They probably found it slightly ticklish, even shameful, to accompany grandmother straight to the vauxhall, where she, of course, was capable of committing all sorts of eccentricities, but now in public. However, they themselves had all volunteered to accompany her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">“Why should I rest?</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">I’m not tired; I’ve been sitting for five days as it is.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">And then we’ll go to look at what sort of springs and medicinal waters they’ve got and where they are.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">And then… what was it you said, Praskovya–a “A “Well, if it’s “There are lots of things, grandmother,” Polina hesitated.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">“Eh, you don’t know yourself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">Marfa, you’ll also come with me,” she said to her maid.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">“Why should she go, auntie?” the general suddenly began bustling.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">“And, finally, it’s forbidden; it’s unlikely Potapych will be allowed in the vauxhall either.” “Well, nonsense!</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">Just because she’s a servant, I should abandon her!</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">She’s also a human being; we’ve been riding the rails for a week now, she also wants to see things.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">Who will she go with, if not me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Alone she won’t dare peek outside.” “But, grandmother… ” “What, are you ashamed to come with me? Stay home then, nobody’s inviting you. Look, what a general; I’m a general’s widow myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">And why indeed should I go dragging such a train behind me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">I’ll look at everything with Alexei Ivanovich… ” But des Grieux resolutely insisted that we all escort her, and produced the most amiable phrases about the pleasure of accompanying her and so on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">We all set off. “ It was about a quarter of a mile to the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">The way led us down the chestnut avenue to the green, beyond which one went straight into the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">The general calmed down a bit, because our procession, though eccentric enough, was nevertheless decorous and decent.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">And there was nothing surprising in the fact of an ailing person with paralyzed legs appearing at the spa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">But the general was obviously afraid of the vauxhall: why should an ailing person with paralyzed legs, and an old woman at that, go to the roulette tables?</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Polina and Mlle Blanche walked on either side of her, beside the rolling chair.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Mlle Blanche laughed, was modestly merry, and from time to time even played up quite amiably to grandmother, so that she finally praised her. Polina, on the other hand, was obliged to answer grandmother’s constant and innumerable questions, such as: “Who’s that man walking by?</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">who’s that woman driving by? how big is the town? how big is the garden?</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">What trees are those? What mountains are these? Are there eagles here?</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">What’s that funny roof?” Mr. Astley was walking beside me and whispered to me that he expected much from this morning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Potapych and Marfa walked behind, just after the chair–Potapych in his tailcoat and white tie, but in a peaked cap, and Marfa, a fortyyearold maiden, redcheeked but already beginning to go gray, in a bonnet, a cotton dress, and creaking kidskin shoes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">Grandmother turned and spoke to them very often. Des Grieux and the general lagged behind a little and talked about something with great vehemence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">The general was very downcast; des Grieux talked with a resolute air.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">Maybe he was trying to encourage the general; obviously he was giving him advice.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">But earlier grandmother had already uttered the fatal phrase: “I won’t give you any money.” This news may have seemed incredible to des Grieux, but the general knew his aunt.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">I noticed that des Grieux and Mlle Blanche continued to exchange winks. I caught sight of the prince and the German traveler at the very end of the avenue: they lagged behind and made off from us somewhere.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">We arrived at the vauxhall in triumph. The doorman and the attendants showed the same deference as the servants in the hotel. They looked at us, however, with curiosity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">Grandmother first of all ordered them to carry her around all the rooms; some things she praised, to others she remained completely indifferent; about everything she asked questions.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">They finally reached the gaming rooms. The footman who was standing guard by the closed doors suddenly, as if in astonishment, flung them open.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">Grandmother’s appearance in the gambling hall made a deep impression on the public. There were maybe a hundred and fifty or two hundred players crowding in several rows around the roulette tables and at the other end of the room where the table for Grandmother observed all this from a distance, with wild curiosity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">She liked it very much that the thieves were removed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">Grandmother began by examining the players. She asked me sharp, abrupt questions in a halfwhisper: who’s that man? who’s that woman? She especially liked one very young man at the end of the table, who played a very big game, staked thousands, and had already won, as the whisper went around, up to forty thousand francs, which lay in a heap before him, in gold and banknotes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">He was pale; his eyes flashed and his hands trembled; he staked now without any calculation, as much as his hands snatched up, and yet he kept winning and winning, raking and raking it all in.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">Attendants bustled about him, put a chair behind him, cleared a space around him so that he would have more room and not be crowded–all this in expectation of a rich reward.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">Certain players, when they’re winning, will sometimes give them money without counting, just like that, out of joy, also as much as their hand snatches from their pocket.</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">A little Pole had already settled himself next to the young man, bustling with all his might, and whispered something to him, respectfully but constantly, probably telling him how to stake, advising and directing the play–naturally, also hoping for a handout afterwards.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">But the gambler scarcely looked at him, staking at random and raking it all in. He was obviously becoming flustered.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">Grandmother observed him for several minutes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">“Tell him,” grandmother suddenly fluttered up, giving me a nudge, “tell him to quit, to take the money and leave quickly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">He’ll lose, he’ll lose everything now!” she fussed, nearly breathless with agitation. “Where’s Potapych?</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">Send Potapych to him! Tell him, tell him,” she nudged me, “no, where indeed is Potapych?</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">“How vexing! The man’s lost, which means he wants it that way himself… I can’t watch him, I’m all upset. What a dolt!” And grandmother quickly turned in another direction. There, to the left, on the other side of the table, among the players, a young lady could be noticed and beside her some sort of dwarf.</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">Who this dwarf was, I don’t know: a relation of hers perhaps, or else just brought along for effect. I had noticed the lady before; she came to the gaming table every day at one in the afternoon and left at exactly two; she played for one hour every day.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">They knew her by now and offered her a chair at once.</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">She would take some gold from her pocket, some thousandfranc notes, and begin to stake quietly, coolly, with calculation, marking the numbers on a paper with her pencil and trying to find the system by which the chances were grouped at the moment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">She staked significant amounts.</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">Every day she won one, two, at the most three thousand francs, not more, and, having won, she immediately left.</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">Grandmother studied her for a long time. “Well, that one’s not going to lose!</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">that one there’s not going to lose!</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">What is she? You don’t know? Who is she?” “A Frenchwoman, must be, or the like,” I whispered. “Ah, you can tell a bird by its flight.</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">You can see her little nails are sharpened.</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">Now explain to me what every turn means and how to stake.” I explained to grandmother, as far as possible, the meaning of the numerous combinations of stakes, “And what is “It’s “Fancy that!</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">And I don’t get anything?” “No, grandmother, if you staked on “What, thirtyfive times? And does it come up often?</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">The fools, why don’t they stake on it?” “The odds are thirtysix to one, grandmother.” “That’s rubbish! Potapych! Potapych! Wait, I have money on me–here!” She took a tightly stuffed purse from her pocket and took out a friedrich d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">“Here, stake it right now on “Grandmother, “Eh, lies, go on, stake!” “As you wish, but it may not come up till evening, you’ll lose as much as a thousand, such things happen.” “Eh, nonsense, nonsense!</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">Nothing ventured, nothing gained.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">What? you lost? Stake again!” We lost the second friedrich d’or; staked a third.</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">Grandmother could barely sit still, she simply fastened her burning eyes on the ball bouncing over the grooves of the turning wheel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">We lost the third as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">Grandmother was beside herself, she simply couldn’t sit still, she even banged her fist on the table when the croupier announced “Drat it!” grandmother said angrily, “won’t that cursed little “Grandmother!” “Stake them, stake them!</sentence>
			<sentence num="109">They’re not yours.” I staked two friedrichs d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="110">The ball rolled around the wheel for a while, then began bouncing over the grooves. Grandmother froze and squeezed my hand, and suddenly–plop!</sentence>
			<sentence num="111">“ “You see, you see!” grandmother quickly turned to me, beaming all over and very pleased.</sentence>
			<sentence num="112">“I told you, I told you! The Lord himself put it into my head to stake two gold pieces. Well, how much will I get now? Why don’t they give it to me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="113">Potapych, Marfa, where are they?</sentence>
			<sentence num="114">Where have all our people gone? Potapych, Potapych!” “Later, grandmother,” I whispered.</sentence>
			<sentence num="115">“Potapych is by the door, they won’t let him in here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="116">Look, grandmother, they’re giving you your money, take it!” They tossed her a heavy roll of fifty friedrichs d’or sealed in dark blue paper and counted out another twenty unsealed friedrichs d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="117">I raked it all towards grandmother. “ “Lord!</sentence>
			<sentence num="118">we’re too late! They’re about to spin it!</sentence>
			<sentence num="119">Stake, stake!” grandmother fussed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="120">“Don’t dawdle, be quick,” she was getting beside herself, nudging me with all her might.</sentence>
			<sentence num="121">“Stake on what, grandmother?” “On “Collect yourself, grandmother! Sometimes it doesn’t come up once in two hundred turns!</sentence>
			<sentence num="122">I assure you, you’ll lose all your capital.” “Eh, lies, lies!</sentence>
			<sentence num="123">stake it! Don’t wag your tongue!</sentence>
			<sentence num="124">I know what I’m doing.” Grandmother was even shaking with frenzy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="125">“According to the rules, you’re not allowed to stake more than twelve friedrichs d’or at a time on “How not allowed?</sentence>
			<sentence num="126">You wouldn’t be lying, would you?</sentence>
			<sentence num="127">Moosieu, moosieu!” she began nudging the croupier, who was sitting just to her left and preparing to spin, “ I hastened to explain her question in French.</sentence>
			<sentence num="128">“ “Well, no help for it, stake twelve.” “ The wheel spun, and thirteen came up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="129">We lost!</sentence>
			<sentence num="130">“Again! again! again! stake again!” cried grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="131">I no longer objected and, shrugging my shoulders, staked another twelve friedrichs d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="132">The wheel spun for a long time. Grandmother simply trembled as she watched it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="133">“Does she really think she’ll win again on “ “So there!!</sentence>
			<sentence num="134">!” grandmother turned to me in furious triumph. I myself was a gambler; I felt it that same moment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="135">My hands and feet were trembling, my head throbbed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="136">Of course, it was a rare case that As grandmother had won the most significant sum, they paid her with particular attention and deference.</sentence>
			<sentence num="137">She was to receive exactly four hundred and twenty friedrichs d’or, that is, four thousand florins and twenty friedrichs d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="138">She was given the twenty friedrichs d’or in gold and the four thousand in banknotes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="139">This time grandmother did not call Potapych; she was otherwise occupied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="140">She didn’t even nudge me or tremble outwardly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="141">She trembled–if it’s possible to put it so–inwardly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="142">She was all concentrated on something, aiming at it: “Alexei Ivanovich!</sentence>
			<sentence num="143">he said one can stake only four thousand florins a time?</sentence>
			<sentence num="144">Here, take and put this whole four thousand on red,” grandmother decided.</sentence>
			<sentence num="145">It was useless to try talking her out of it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="146">The wheel spun.</sentence>
			<sentence num="147">“ Again a win of four thousand florins, meaning eight in all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="148">“Give me four here, and put four on red again,” grandmother commanded.</sentence>
			<sentence num="149">I staked four thousand again. “ “A total of twelve! Give it all here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="150">Pour the gold here, into this purse, and put away the banknotes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="151">“Enough! Home! Roll on!”</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="11" name="CHAPTER XI">
			<sentence num="1"> THE CHAIR WAS ROLLED to the door at the other end of the room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">Grandmother was beaming.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">All our people crowded around her at once with congratulations.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">However eccentric grandmother’s behavior was, her triumph covered up a lot, and the general no longer feared compromising himself in public by being related to such an odd woman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">With a condescending and familiarly cheerful smile, as if placating a child, he congratulated grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">However, he was evidently struck, as were all the spectators.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">The people around were talking and pointing at grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">Many walked past her in order to get a closer look.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">Mr. Astley, standing to one side, was talking about her with two Englishmen of his acquaintance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">Several majestic spectators, ladies, gazed at her as at some wonder, with majestic perplexity.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">Des Grieux simply dissolved in smiles and congratulations.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">“ “ “Yes, ma’am, I just up and won twelve thousand florins!</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Twelve, nothing, what about the gold?</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">With the gold it comes out to nearly thirteen.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">How much is that in our money?</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">Some six thousand, eh?” I reported that it was over seven and, with the exchange what it was, maybe even eight.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">“No joking, eight thousand!</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">And you dunderheads sit here and do nothing!</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">Potapych, Marfa, did you see?” “Dearie, but how can it be?</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">Eight thousand roubles!” Marfa exclaimed, twining about.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">“Take, here’s five gold pieces from me for each of you, here!” Potapych and Marfa rushed to kiss her hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">“The porters get one friedrich d’or each.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">Give them a gold piece each, Alexei Ivanovich.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">What’s that attendant bowing for, and the other one also?</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">Congratulating me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">Give them each a friedrich d’or as well.” “ “Give him a friedrich d’or as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">No, give him two; well, enough, there’ll be no end to it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Up and carry!</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">Praskovya,” she turned to Polina Alexandrovna, “tomorrow I’ll buy you stuff for a dress, and also for this Mlle… how’s she called, Mlle Blanche, or something, I’ll also buy her stuff for a dress.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">Translate, Praskovya!” “ “Fedosya, I’m thinking how surprised Fedosya will be now,” said grandmother, remembering her acquaintance, the general’s nanny.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">“She should also be given money for a dress.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Hey, Alexei Ivanovich, Alexei Ivanovich, give something to this beggar!” Some ragamuffin with a bent back was going down the road and looking at us.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">“Maybe he’s not a beggar, grandmother, but some sort of rascal.” “Give!</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">give! give him a gulden!” I went over and gave it to him. He gazed at me in wild perplexity, though he silently took the gulden. He reeked of wine.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">“And you, Alexei Ivanovich, have you tried your luck yet?” “No, grandmother.” “Your eyes were burning, I saw it.” “I’ll try it yet, grandmother, for certain, later on.” “And stake directly on “Only twenty friedrichs d’or, grandmother.” “Not much.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">I’ll lend you fifty friedrichs d’or, if you like.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">Here’s that same roll, take it, and you, dearie, don’t get your hopes up, I won’t give you anything!” she suddenly turned to the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">The man was as if bowled over, but he said nothing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">Des Grieux frowned.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">“ “A beggar, a beggar, again a beggar!” cried grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">“Alexei Ivanovich, give this one a gulden, too.” This time we met a grayhaired old man on a wooden leg, in some sort of longskirted blue frock coat and with a long cane in his hand.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">He looked like an old soldier. But when I offered him a gulden, he stepped back and examined me menacingly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“ “Eh, the fool!” cried grandmother, waving her hand.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">“Drive on! I’m hungry!</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">I’ll have dinner right now, then loll about for a bit and go back again.” “You want to gamble again, grandmother?” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“What do you think? You all sit here and mope, so I’ve got to look at you?” “ “ “What is it to all of you?</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">It’s my money I’ll be losing, not yours! And where is that Mr. Astley?” she asked me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">“He stayed at the vauxhall, grandmother.” “A pity; he’s such a nice man.” On reaching home, grandmother, meeting the manager while still on the stairs, called to him and boasted of her win; then she called Fedosya, gave her three friedrichs d’or and ordered dinner served.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">Fedosya and Marfa simply dissolved before her during dinner.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">“I’m watching you, dearie,” Marfa rattled out, “and I say to Potapych, what is it our dearie means to do?</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">And all that money on the table, all that money, saints alive!</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">in my whole life I never saw so much money, and gentlefolk all around, nothing but gentlefolk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">How is it, Potapych, I say, it’s all such gentlefolk here? Mother of God, I think, help her. I’m praying for you, dearie, and my heart sinks, it just sinks, I’m trembling, I’m trembling all over.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">Grant her, Lord, I think, and so here the Lord sent it to you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">And till now I’m still trembling, dearie, just trembling all over.” “Alexei Ivanovich, after dinner, at around four, get ready and we’ll go.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Meanwhile, goodbye–oh, yes, and don’t forget to send me some little doctor, I also have to drink the waters.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">Or else you may forget.” I left grandmother’s as if in a daze. I tried to imagine what would happen now with all our people and what turn affairs would take. I saw clearly that they (the general mainly) had not yet managed to collect their senses, even from the first impression.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">The fact of grandmother’s appearance, instead of the telegram about her death (and therefore about the inheritance as well) that had been expected at any moment, had so shattered the whole system of their intentions and alreadymade decisions, that they treated grandmother’s further exploits at roulette with decided perplexity and a sort of stupor, which had come over them all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">And yet this second fact was almost more important than the first, because, though grandmother had twice repeated that she would give no money to the general, who could tell–all the same they should not lose hope yet.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">Des Grieux, who was involved in all the general’s affairs, had not.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">I was sure that Mlle Blanche, who was also quite involved (what else: a general’s wife and a considerable inheritance!)</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">would not lose hope and would use all the seductions of coquetry on grandmother–in contrast to the proud and unyielding Polina, who was not given to tenderness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">But now, now, when grandmother had performed such exploits at roulette, now, when grandmother’s personality was stamped so clearly and typically before them (an obstinate, domineering old woman, All these considerations wandered through my head while I was going up the central stairway from grandmother’s to the topmost floor, to my little room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">All this concerned me greatly; though, of course, I could guess in advance the main, the thickest threads connecting the actors before me, I still did not ultimately know all the means and secrets of this game. Polina was never fully trusting with me. Though, true, it did happen that she would open her heart to me occasionally, as if inadvertently, I noticed that often, even almost always, after being open, she either turned everything she had said to ridicule, or deliberately made it look confused and false.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Oh, she concealed a lot! In any case, I sensed that the finale was approaching for this whole mysterious and tense situation. One more stroke and everything would be finished and revealed. About my own fate, which was also caught up in it all, I almost didn’t worry.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">I was in a strange mood: in my pocket a total of twenty friedrichs d’or; I’m far away in a foreign land, with no post and no means of existence, no hopes, no plans and–it doesn’t worry me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">If it hadn’t been for the thought of Polina, I would simply have surrendered myself entirely to the comic interest of the coming denouement and laughed my head off. But Polina confounds me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">Her fate is being decided, I can feel that, but, I confess, it’s not at all her fate that troubles me. I’d like to penetrate her secrets; I’d like her to come to me and say: “I love you,” and if not, if that madness is unthinkable, then… well, what should I wish for? Do I know what to wish for? I’m as if lost myself; all I need is to be near her, in her aura, in her radiance, forever, always, all my life.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Beyond that I know nothing!</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">And can I possibly leave her? On the third floor, in their corridor, it was as if something nudged me. I turned and, twenty or more paces away, saw Polina coming out the door. She seemed to have been waiting and watching for me, and immediately beckoned to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">“Polina Alexandrovna… ” “Quiet!” she warned. “Imagine,” I whispered, “it’s as if something just nudged me in the side; I turn around–it’s you! As if you give off some kind of electricity!” “Take this letter,” Polina said with a preoccupied and frowning air, probably without hearing what I had just said, “and deliver it personally to Mr. Astley right away.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">Be quick, I beg you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">No reply is needed. He himself… ” She didn’t finish. “To Mr. Astley?” I repeated in astonishment. But Polina had already disappeared through the door.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">“Aha, so they correspond!” Naturally, I ran at once to look for Mr. Astley, first in his hotel, where I didn’t find him, then in the vauxhall, where I ran around all the rooms, and finally, in vexation, almost in despair, on my way home, I met him by chance in a cavalcade of some English men and ladies, on horseback.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">I beckoned to him, stopped him, and gave him the letter. We had no time even to exchange glances. But I suspect that Mr. Astley deliberately hastened to urge his horse on. Was I tormented by jealousy?</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">I was indeed in the most broken state of mind.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">I didn’t even want to know what they corresponded about. So he was her confidant! “A friend he may be,” I thought, and that was clear (and when had he found time to become one?</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">), “but is there love in it?” “Of course not,” reason whispered to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">But reason alone is not enough in such cases. In any case, this, too, was to be clarified.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">The business was becoming unpleasantly complicated. I no sooner entered the hotel than the doorman and the manager, coming out of his room, informed me that I was being asked for, looked for, that three times there had been an inquiry about where I was, and a request that I go as quickly as possible to the general’s suite.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">I was in the nastiest state of mind. In the general’s study, besides the general himself, I found des Grieux and Mlle Blanche, alone, without her mother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">The mother was decidedly a dummy personage, used only for display; when it came to real The three of them were hotly conferring about something, and the door of the study was even shut, something that had never happened before.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">Approaching the door, I heard loud voices–the brazen and caustic talk of des Grieux, the impudently abusive and furious shouting of Blanche, and the pitiful voice of the general, who was apparently trying to justify himself for something.</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">On my appearance, they all seemed to restrain themselves and put themselves to rights.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">Des Grieux put his hair to rights and made his angry face into a smiling one–with that nasty, officially courteous French smile I hate so much.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">The general, crushed and at a loss, assumed a dignified air, but somehow mechanically.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">Mlle Blanche alone made scarcely a change in her angerflashing physiognomy and only fell silent, directing her gaze at me with impatient expectation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">I will note that till then she had treated me with incredible negligence, had not even responded to my greetings–simply hadn’t noticed me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">“Alexei Ivanovich,” the general began in a gently upbraiding tone, “allow me to declare to you that it is strange, strange in the highest degree… in short, your behavior regarding me and my family… in short, strange in the highest degree… ” “ “But how, how?” I interrupted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">“Good heavens, you’ve undertaken to be the guide (or how do they say?)</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">of this old woman, “And then,” the general picked up, “then you will ruin the entire family!</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">Me and my family, we’re her heirs, she has no closer relations. I’ll tell you frankly: my affairs are in disarray, extreme disarray. You partly know yourself… If she loses a considerable sum, or even perhaps the whole fortune (oh, God! ), what will become of them then, of my children!” (the general turned to des Grieux) “of me!” (He looked at Mlle Blanche, who turned away from him with contempt.)</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">“Alexei Ivanovich, save us, save us!… ” “But how, General, tell me, how can I… What do I amount to here?” “Refuse, refuse, drop her!… ” “Then she’ll find somebody else!” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">“ “But how can I do that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">If you were to take it upon yourself, M. des Grieux,” I added as naïvely as I could.</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">Here I noticed the quick, fiery, questioning glance Mlle Blanche gave des Grieux.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">In des Grieux’s own face something peculiar flashed, something frank, which he was unable to hold back.</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">“That’s just it, that she won’t take me now!” des Grieux cried, waving his hand.</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">“If only!… later… ” Des Grieux glanced quickly and significantly at Mlle Blanche. “ The general jumped up after her–precisely jumped: “Alexei Ivanovich, forgive me for speaking to you like that earlier, I meant to say something else… I beg you, I implore you, I bow down before you Russianstyle–you, you alone can save us!</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">Mlle de Cominges and I implore you–you understand?</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">you do understand?” he implored, indicating Mlle Blanche to me with his eyes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">He was very pitiful. At that moment there came three quiet and respectful knocks at the door; they opened–the floorboy had knocked, and a few steps behind him stood Potapych.</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">The ambassadors were from grandmother. There was a request to find me and deliver me immediately–“she being angry,” Potapych informed me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">“But it’s still only halfpast three!” “She couldn’t sleep, kept tossing, then suddenly got up, demanded her chair, and sent for you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">She’s already on the porch, sir… ” “ Indeed, I found grandmother already on the porch, losing patience over my absence. She couldn’t wait till four o’clock. “Well, lift me up!” she cried, and we set off again for the roulette tables.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="12" name="CHAPTER XII">
			<sentence num="1"> GRANDMOTHER WAS IN AN impatient and irritable state of mind; it was clear that roulette had lodged itself firmly in her head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">She paid no attention to anything else, and was generally extremely distracted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">For instance, she didn’t ask questions about anything on the way, as she had earlier.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">Seeing a very rich carriage that raced past us like the wind, she raised her hand and asked: “What’s that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">Whose is it?”–but didn’t seem to hear my reply; her pensiveness was constantly broken by abrupt and impatient movements and actions.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">When I pointed out Baron and Baroness Wurmerhelm in the distance, as we were approaching the vauxhall, she looked distractedly and said quite indifferently: “Ah!”–and, turning quickly to Potapych and Marfa, who were walking behind her, said sharply: “Well, why are you tagging along?</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">You needn’t be taken every time!</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">Go home!</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">You’re enough for me,” she added to me, when the other two hastily bowed and returned home.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">Grandmother was already expected in the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">She was at once allotted the same place next to the croupier.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">It seems to me that these croupiers, who are always so decorous and pretend to be ordinary officials for whom it is decidedly almost all the same whether the bank wins or loses, are not at all indifferent to the bank’s losses and, of course, are furnished with certain instructions for attracting gamblers and keeping better watch over the establishment’s interests–for which they certainly receive prizes and awards.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">At any rate they already looked upon grandmother as a nice little victim.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">Thereupon, what had been assumed of us–happened.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Here’s how it went.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">Grandmother fell directly on “How many times have we lost?” she asked finally, grinding her teeth in impatience.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">“That was the twelfth stake, grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">We’ve lost a hundred and fortyfour friedrichs d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">I tell you, grandmother, it may not be till evening… ” “Silence!” grandmother interrupted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">“Stake on Red came up, but the “See, see!” whispered grandmother, “we won back almost everything we lost.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">Stake again on But by the fifth time grandmother had become quite bored.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">“To hell with it, drop that nasty little “Grandmother!</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">it’s too much, what if red doesn’t come up?” I implored; but grandmother nearly hit me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">(However, she nudged me so hard that one could almost call it beating.)</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">There was nothing to be done, I staked all the four thousand guldens we had won earlier on red.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">The wheel spun. Grandmother sat calmly and proudly erect, not doubting the certainty of winning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">“ At first grandmother didn’t understand, but when she saw the croupier rake in her four thousand guldens along with everything that was on the table, and learned that the “Saints alive!</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">The cursed thing had to pop up just now!” grandmother yelled.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">“What a fiendish, fiendish thing!</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">It’s you! It’s all you!” she fell upon me ferociously, shoving me. “You talked me out of it.” “Grandmother, I talked sense to you, how can I be responsible for all the chances?” “I’ll give you your chances!” she whispered threateningly. “Get out of here!” “Goodbye, grandmother,” I turned to leave.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">“Alexei Ivanovich, Alexei Ivanovich, stay!</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Where are you going? Well, what is it?</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">what is it? Look, he’s angry! Fool! Stay, stay awhile, don’t be angry, I’m a fool myself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">Well, tell me, what am I to do now?” “I won’t venture to tell you, grandmother, because you’re going to accuse me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">Play on your own; order me, and I’ll stake.” “Well, well!</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">so stake another four thousand guldens on red!</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">Here’s my wallet, take it.” She took the wallet from her pocket and gave it to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">“Well, take it quickly, there’s twenty thousand roubles in cash here.” “Grandmother,” I whispered, “such amounts… ” “I’ll win it back if it kills me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">Stake!” We staked and lost.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">“Stake, stake, stake the whole eight thousand!” “I can’t, grandmother, the biggest stake is four!… ” “Stake four then!” This time we won.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">Grandmother took heart. “See, see!” she nudged me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">“Stake four again.” We staked and lost; staked again and lost again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“Grandmother, the whole twelve thousand is gone,” I reported.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">“I see it’s gone,” she said in some sort of calm fury, if I may put it so, “I see, dearie, I see,” she muttered, staring fixedly in front of her and as if pondering.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">“Eh, even if it kills me, stake another four thousand guldens!” “But we have no money, grandmother; there are some Russian five percent notes and some postal money orders in the wallet, but no money.” “And in the purse?” “Only small change left, grandmother.” “Do they have exchange bureaus here?</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">I was told I could cash any Russian papers here,” grandmother asked resolutely.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">“Oh, as much as you like!</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">But you’ll lose so much on the exchange that… the Jew himself will be horrified.” “Rubbish!</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">I’ll win it back. Take me. Call those blockheads!” I rolled the chair away, the porters appeared, and we rolled out of the vauxhall. “Hurry, hurry!” grandmother commanded.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">“Show the way, Alexei Ivanovich, the shortest… is it far?” “Two steps away, grandmother.” But at the turn from the green into the avenue, we met our whole company: the general, des Grieux, and Mlle Blanche with her mama.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">Polina Alexandrovna was not with them, nor was Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">“Well, well, well! no stopping!” shouted grandmother. “Well, what do you care?</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">I have no time for you!” I walked behind; des Grieux sprang over to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">“She lost all she won in the morning and blew twelve thousand guldens of her own.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">We’re on our way to exchange the five percent notes,” I whispered to him hurriedly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Des Grieux stamped his foot and dashed to tell the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">We went on rolling grandmother. “Stop her, stop her!” the general whispered in a frenzy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">!” cried grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">“I tell you, I have no time!” “Here we are, grandmother!” I cried. “This it it!” We rolled up to the house where the banker’s office was.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">I went to exchange the notes; grandmother stayed waiting by the entrance; des Grieux, the general, and Blanche stood to one side, not knowing what to do.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">Grandmother looked at them wrathfully, and they went off down the road to the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">I was offered such terrible terms that I didn’t dare accept and went back to grandmother to ask for instructions.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">“Ah, the robbers!” she cried, clasping her hands. “Well!</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Never mind! Exchange them!” she cried resolutely.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">“Wait, call the banker to me!” “Maybe one of the clerks, grandmother?” “All right, a clerk, it’s all the same.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">Ah, the robbers!” The clerk agreed to come out, having learned that he had been asked by a paralyzed old countess who couldn’t walk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">Grandmother reproached him for thievery, at length, wrathfully, and loudly, and bargained with him in a mixture of Russian, French, and German, with me helping to translate.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">The grave clerk kept looking at the two of us and silently wagging his head. He gazed at grandmother even with a much too intent curiosity–which was impolite. Finally, he began to smile. “Well, away with you!” cried grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">“Choke on my money!</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">Exchange with him, Alexei Ivanovich, there’s no time, otherwise we could go elsewhere… ” “The clerk says others will give still less.” I don’t remember the figures exactly, but it was terrible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">I exchanged about twelve thousand florins in gold and notes, took the receipt, and brought it to grandmother.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">“Well!</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">well!</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">well!</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">No point in counting it,” she waved her hands, “quick, quick, quick!” “I’ll never stake on that cursed This time I tried as hard as I could to persuade her to make smaller stakes, insisting that, with a turn of the chances, there would always be a moment for staking a big amount.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">But she was so impatient that, though she agreed at first, it was impossible to hold her back during the play.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">As soon as she began to win stakes of ten or twenty friedrichs d’or, “Well, there! Well, there!” she began nudging me, “well, there, we’ve won–if we’d staked four thousand instead of ten, we’d have won four thousand, and what now?</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">It’s all you, all you!” And vexed as I was, watching her play, I finally decided to keep quiet and give no more advice.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">Suddenly des Grieux sprang over. The three of them were nearby; I noticed that Mlle Blanche and her mama were standing to one side, exchanging courtesies with the little prince.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">The general was obviously out of favor, almost in the doghouse.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">Blanche didn’t even want to look at him, though he fidgeted about her with all his might. Poor general! He turned pale, red, trembled, and even no longer followed grandmother’s play.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">Blanche and the little prince finally left; the general ran after them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">“ “And how, then? Go on, teach me!” grandmother turned to him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">Des Grieux suddenly began babbling rapidly in French, giving advice, fussing, saying one had to wait for the chance, started calculating some numbers… Grandmother understood nothing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">He turned to me constantly, asking me to translate; jabbed his finger at the table, pointing, finally snatched a pencil and was beginning to work something out on paper.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">Grandmother finally lost patience. “Well, away, away with you! it’s all rubbish! “ “Well, stake once as he says,” grandmother told me, “let’s see; maybe it will really work.” Des Grieux wanted only to distract her from big stakes: he suggested staking on numbers singly and in groups.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">I staked, at his direction, one friedrich d’or on each of the series of odd numbers from one to twelve, and five friedrichs d’or on groups of numbers between twelve and eighteen, and between eighteen and twentyfour: in all we staked sixteen friedrichs d’or.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">The wheel spun. “ “What a blockhead!” cried grandmother, turning to des Grieux. “Vile little Frenchman that you are! You and your fiendish advice!</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">Away, away! He doesn’t understand a thing, and he pokes his nose into it anyway!” Terribly offended, des Grieux shrugged his shoulders, gave grandmother a contemptuous look, and walked off.</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">He felt ashamed now that he had gotten involved; he just couldn’t help it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">An hour later, despite all our efforts, we had lost everything.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">“Home!” cried grandmother. She didn’t say a word till we got to the avenue.</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">In the avenue and already approaching the hotel, exclamations began to escape her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">“What a fool! what a great big fool!</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">You old fool, you!” We had only just entered the suite: “Bring me tea!” grandmother cried, “and get ready at once!</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">We’re going!” “Where would you be pleased to be going, dearie?” Marfa tried to ask.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">“What business is that of yours?</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">To your last, shoemaker!</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">Potapych, pack up everything, all the luggage! We’re going back to Moscow! I’ve “Fifteen thousand, dearie! My God!” cried Potapych, clasping his hands touchingly, probably hoping to oblige.</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">“Well, well, you fool! None of this sniveling! Silence! Get ready!</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">The bill, quickly, quickly!” “The next train leaves at halfpast nine, grandmother,” I reported, to stop her furor.</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">“And what is it now?” “Halfpast seven.” “How vexing! Well, never mind!</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">Alexei Ivanovich, I haven’t a kopeck.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">Here are two more notes, run off to that place, exhange them for me. Otherwise I’ll have nothing for the road.” I went.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">Half an hour later, on returning to the hotel, I found all our people at grandmother’s.</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">Having learned that grandmother was leaving altogether for Moscow, they seemed to be even more struck than by her losses. Suppose that going away would save her fortune, but what would become of the general now? Who would pay des Grieux?</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">Mlle Blanche certainly wouldn’t wait until grandmother died, and would probably slip away now with the little prince or somebody else.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">They were all standing in front of her, comforting her, trying to talk sense into her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="109">Polina again was not there.</sentence>
			<sentence num="110">Grandmother was shouting furiously at them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="111">“Leave me alone, you devils! What business is it of yours? Why is this goatbeard getting at me?” she shouted at des Grieux.</sentence>
			<sentence num="112">“And you, you shank of a girl, what do you want?” she turned to Mlle Blanche.</sentence>
			<sentence num="113">“What are you fussing about?” “ “ “Ah, so you’re counting on my death?” grandmother screamed at the general.</sentence>
			<sentence num="114">“Get out! Throw them all out, Alexei Ivanovich! Is it any of your business?</sentence>
			<sentence num="115">I’ve blown my money, not yours!” The general shrugged his shoulders, stooped, and left.</sentence>
			<sentence num="116">Des Grieux followed. “Call Praskovya,” grandmother told Marfa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="117">Five minutes later Marfa returned with Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="118">All this time Polina had been sitting in her room with the children and, it seems, had purposely decided not to go out all day.</sentence>
			<sentence num="119">Her face was serious, sad, and preoccupied.</sentence>
			<sentence num="120">“Praskovya,” grandmother began, “is it true, what I learned from someone today, that your fool of a stepfather supposedly wants to marry that silly French fidget–an actress, isn’t she, or something still worse?</sentence>
			<sentence num="121">Tell me, is it true?” “I don’t know for certain, grandmother,” Polina answered, “but from the words of Mlle Blanche herself, who finds concealment unnecessary, I conclude… ” “Enough!” grandmother interrupted energetically, “I understand everything!</sentence>
			<sentence num="122">I always reckoned he was up to just that, and always considered him the emptiest and flightiest of men.</sentence>
			<sentence num="123">He goes around swaggering that he’s a general (he got the rank after he retired as a colonel), and putting on airs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="124">I know it all, my dear, how you sent telegram after telegram to Moscow–‘Will the old crone turn her toes up soon?’ They were waiting for the inheritance; without money, that mean wench–what’s her name?–de Cominges or something, wouldn’t even take him as a lackey, with false teeth at that.</sentence>
			<sentence num="125">They say she has heaps of money herself, lends it on interest, having earned it in a nice way.</sentence>
			<sentence num="126">I don’t blame you, Praskovya; it wasn’t you who sent the telegrams; nor do I want to remember old wrongs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="127">I know what a nasty character you’ve got–a wasp!</sentence>
			<sentence num="128">it swells when you sting, but I feel sorry for you, because I loved your late mother Katerina. Well, do you want to drop all this here and come with me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="129">You’ve got nowhere to go; and it’s improper for you to be with them now.</sentence>
			<sentence num="130">Wait!” grandmother interrupted Polina, who was about to begin a reply, “I haven’t finished yet.</sentence>
			<sentence num="131">I won’t demand anything of you. My house in Moscow you know–it’s a palace, you can have a whole floor and not come down to see me for weeks, if you don’t fancy my character.</sentence>
			<sentence num="132">Well, do you want to or not?” “Allow me to ask you first: do you really mean to leave right now?” “Do you think I’m joking, dearie?</sentence>
			<sentence num="133">I said I’d leave, and I’ll leave.</sentence>
			<sentence num="134">I’ve dumped fifteen thousand roubles today at your thricecursed roulette.</sentence>
			<sentence num="135">Five years ago I promised to replace the wooden church on my estate near Moscow with a stone one, and instead I whistled it away here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="136">Now, dearie, I’m going to go and build that church.” “And the waters, grandmother?</sentence>
			<sentence num="137">Haven’t you come to take the waters?” “Eh, you and your waters! Don’t vex me, Praskovya; are you doing it on purpose, or what?</sentence>
			<sentence num="138">Tell me, will you come along?” “I thank you very, very much, grandmother,” Polina began with feeling, “for the refuge you’re offering me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="139">You’ve partly guessed my situation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="140">I’m so grateful that, believe me, I may even come to you soon; but now there are reasons… important ones… and I can’t decide at once, this minute.</sentence>
			<sentence num="141">If you were staying two weeks… ” “You mean you don’t want to?” “I mean I can’t.</sentence>
			<sentence num="142">Besides, in any case I can’t leave my brother and sister, and since… since… since they may indeed be all but abandoned, then… if you’ll take me with the little ones, grandmother, I’ll certainly come to you, and, believe me, I’ll come to deserve it of you,” she added warmly, “but without the children I can’t, grandmother.” “Well, don’t snivel!” (Polina had never thought of sniveling, and she never cried.)</sentence>
			<sentence num="143">“There’ll be room for the chicks as well; it’s a big chicken coop.</sentence>
			<sentence num="144">Besides, it’s time they went to school. Well, so you’re not coming now? Well, Praskovya, watch out!</sentence>
			<sentence num="145">I’d like to wish you well, but I know why you’re not coming.</sentence>
			<sentence num="146">I know everything, Praskovya! That little Frenchman won’t bring you any good.” Polina flushed. I gave a start.</sentence>
			<sentence num="147">(Everybody knows!</sentence>
			<sentence num="148">I alone, therefore, know nothing!)</sentence>
			<sentence num="149">“Well, well, don’t frown. I won’t embroider on it. Only watch out that nothing bad happens, understand?</sentence>
			<sentence num="150">You’re a smart girl; I’d be sorry for you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="151">Well, enough, I don’t even want to look at you all!</sentence>
			<sentence num="152">Go! Goodbye!” “I’ll still come to see you off, grandmother,” said Polina. “No need to; don’t bother me, I’m sick of you all.” Polina kissed grandmother’s hand, but she pulled her hand away and kissed Polina on the cheek.</sentence>
			<sentence num="153">As she passed me, Polina glanced at me quickly and at once turned away.</sentence>
			<sentence num="154">“Well, goodbye to you, too, Alexei Ivanovich!</sentence>
			<sentence num="155">It’s only an hour till the train. And you’re tired of me, I think.</sentence>
			<sentence num="156">Here, take these fifty gold pieces.” “I humbly thank you, grandmother, I’m ashamed to… ” “Well, well!” cried grandmother, but so energetically and menacingly that I didn’t dare refuse and accepted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="157">“In Moscow, when you’re running around without a job, come to me; I’ll recommend you to someone.</sentence>
			<sentence num="158">Well, out with you!” I went to my room and lay down on the bed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="159">I think I lay for half an hour on my back, my hands thrust behind my head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="160">The catastrophe had broken out, there was something to think about.</sentence>
			<sentence num="161">I decided imperatively to talk with Polina tomorrow. Ah! the little Frenchman? So then it’s true!</sentence>
			<sentence num="162">What could there be to it, though? Polina and des Grieux!</sentence>
			<sentence num="163">Lord, what a juxtaposition!</sentence>
			<sentence num="164">All this was simply unbelievable. I suddenly jumped up, beside myself, to go looking for Mr. Astley at once and make him speak at all costs. Here, too, of course, he knows more than I do. Mr. Astley?</sentence>
			<sentence num="165">There’s another riddle for me! But suddenly there came a knock at my door.</sentence>
			<sentence num="166">I looked–Potapych.</sentence>
			<sentence num="167">“Alexei Ivanovich, my dear: the mistress, she’s calling.” “What is it? Is she leaving or something?</sentence>
			<sentence num="168">It’s still twenty minutes till the train.” “She’s restless, my dear, can barely sit still.</sentence>
			<sentence num="169">‘Quick, quick!’–meaning you, my dear; for Christ’s sake, don’t delay.” I raced downstairs at once.</sentence>
			<sentence num="170">Grandmother had already been rolled out to the corridor.</sentence>
			<sentence num="171">She had the wallet in her hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="172">“Alexei Ivanovich, lead the way, come on!… ” “Where to, grandmother?” “It may kill me, but I’ll win back what I lost!</sentence>
			<sentence num="173">Well, march, no questions!</sentence>
			<sentence num="174">They play till midnight there, don’t they?” I was dumbfounded, reflected, but made up my mind at once.</sentence>
			<sentence num="175">“As you will, Antonida Vassilyevna, but I won’t go.” “Why not?</sentence>
			<sentence num="176">What’s this now? Are you all moonstruck or something?” “As you will, but afterwards I’d reproach myself; I don’t want to!</sentence>
			<sentence num="177">I don’t want either to witness it or to participate in it; spare me, Antonida Vassilyevna.</sentence>
			<sentence num="178">Here are your fifty friedrichs d’or back; goodbye!” And, placing the roll of friedrichs d’or right there on a little table next to grandmother’s chair, I bowed and left.</sentence>
			<sentence num="179">“What rubbish!” grandmother cried after me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="180">“Don’t come then, if you please, I’ll find the way myself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="181">Potapych, come with me! Well, pick me up, get going.” I didn’t find Mr. Astley and went back home.</sentence>
			<sentence num="182">Late, past midnight, I learned from Potapych how grandmother’s day had ended.</sentence>
			<sentence num="183">She had lost everything I had exchanged for her earlier, that is, another ten thousand roubles, by our reckoning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="184">That same little Pole to whom she had given two friedrichs d’or had attached himself to her and guided her play the whole time.</sentence>
			<sentence num="185">First, before the little Pole, she had made Potapych stake for her, but soon chased him away; it was then that the little Pole popped up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="186">As luck would have it, he understood Russian and could even chatter in a mixture of three languages, so that they somehow managed to understand each other.</sentence>
			<sentence num="187">Grandmother scolded him mercilessly all the time, and though he constantly “laid himself out at my lady’s feet,” he was “no comparison with you, Alexei Ivanovich,” Potapych recounted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="188">“She treated you</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="13" name="CHAPTER XIII">
			<sentence num="1"> IT’S ALMOST A WHOLE month now since I’ve touched these notes of mine, begun under the effect of strong though disorderly impressions. The catastrophe, the approach of which I anticipated then, did come, but a hundred times more drastically and unexpectedly than I had thought.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">It was all something strange, ugly, and even tragic, at any rate for me. Certain things happened to me that were almost miraculous; so at least I look at them to this day–though from another point of view, and especially judging by the whirl I was then spinning in, they were at most only somewhat out of the ordinary.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">But most miraculous of all for me was the way I regarded these events.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">To this day I don’t understand myself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">And it all flew away like a dream–even my passion, and yet it really was strong and true, but… where has it gone now?</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">Indeed, the thought occasionally flits through my head: “Didn’t I go out of my mind then and spend the whole time sitting in a madhouse somewhere, and maybe I’m sitting there now–so that for me it was all a I collected and reread my pages. (Who knows, maybe so as to convince myself that I hadn’t written them in the madhouse?) Now I’m all alone. Autumn is coming, the leaves are turning yellow.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">I’m sitting in this dreary little town (oh, how dreary little German towns are!</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">), and instead of thinking over the next step, I live under the influence of feelings just past, under the influence of fresh memories, under the influence of all this recent whirl, which drew me into that turbulence then, and threw me out of it again somewhere.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">It still seems to me at times that I’m spinning in the same whirl, and that the storm is about to rush upon me, snatch me up with its wing in passing, and I will again break out of all order and sense of measure, and spin, spin, spin… However, maybe I’ll settle somehow and stop spinning, if I give myself as precise an account as possible of all that happened this month.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">I’m drawn to my pen again; and sometimes there’s nothing at all to do in the evenings. Strangely, in order to occupy myself with at least something, I go to the mangy local library and take out the novels of Paul de Kock{11} (in German translation! ), which I can barely stand, but I read them and–marvel at myself: it’s as if I’m afraid to spoil the charm of what has only just passed by a serious book or some serious occupation. As if this ugly dream and all the impressions it left behind are so dear to me that I’m even afraid to touch it with something new, lest it vanish in smoke!</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">Is it so dear to me, or what? Yes, of course it is; maybe I’ll remember it even forty years later… And so, I set about writing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">However, all this can now be told partially and more briefly: the impressions are not at all the same… First, to finish with grandmother. The next day she definitively lost everything.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">That’s how it had to happen: once that kind of person starts out on this path, then, like sliding down a snowy hill on a sled, it all goes faster and faster. She played all day, until eight o’clock in the evening; I wasn’t present when she played and know it only from hearsay.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">Potapych attended her at the vauxhall the whole day. The little Poles who guided grandmother changed several times that day. She started by chasing away the previous day’s little Pole, whose hair she had pulled, and taking another one, but he turned out to be almost worse.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Having chased that one away and taken back the first one, who hadn’t left and poked about during the whole time of his banishment right there behind her chair, thrusting his head in every moment–she finally fell into decided despair.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">The second chasedaway little Pole also refused to leave; one stationed himself to her right, the other to her left. They quarreled and abused each other all the time over stakes and strategy, called each other But grandmother gained very, very little from having rid herself of the two Poles.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">In their place a third Pole appeared at once to serve her, speaking perfectly pure Russian, dressed like a gentleman, though he smacked of the footman all the same, with enormous mustaches and with By Potapych’s reckoning, grandmother lost in that day a total of ninety thousand roubles, besides the money she had lost the day before.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">All her bonds–the five percent bonds, the state bonds, all the shares she had brought with her–she had cashed one after the other.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">I marveled at her ability to hold out for the whole seven or eight hours, sitting in her chair and hardly ever leaving the table, but Potapych told me that, on some three occasions, she had actually begun to win heavily, and, borne up by renewed hope, had no longer been able to leave.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">However, gamblers know how a man can sit almost around the clock in the same place over cards, without taking his eyes off the right one or the left. Meanwhile, all that day quite decisive things were happening with us in the hotel. In the morning, before eleven o’clock, when grandmother was still at home, our people–that is, the general and des Grieux–resolved upon an ultimate step.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">Learning that grandmother had no thought of leaving, but, on the contrary, was setting out again for the vauxhall, the whole conclave of them (except for Polina) came to talk things over with her definitively and even That same morning I went to see Mr. Astley, or, better to say, I spent the whole morning looking for Mr. Astley, but couldn’t find him anywhere.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">He was neither at home, nor in the vauxhall, nor in the park. He did not dine at his hotel that day. Between four and five, I suddenly saw him coming from the railway platform straight to the Hôtel d’Angleterre.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">He was hurrying and very preoccupied, though it was hard to make out the preoccupation or any sort of perplexity in his face. He offered me his hand affably, with his usual exclamation: “Ah!” but without stopping in the road and continuing on his way at a rather quick pace.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">I tagged along behind him; but he was somehow able to answer me in such a way that I didn’t manage to ask him about anything. Besides, for some reason I was terribly ashamed to ask about Polina; he didn’t ask a word about her himself. I told him about grandmother; he listened attentively and gravely, and shrugged his shoulders.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">“She’ll lose everything,” I observed. “Oh, yes,” he replied, “she already went to play earlier, as I was leaving, and so I knew for certain that she’d lose. If I have time I’ll stop by the vauxhall to have a look, because it’s curious… ” “Where did you go?” I cried, amazed that I hadn’t asked till then. “I was in Frankfurt.” “On business?” “Yes, on business.” Well, what more was there for me to ask?</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">However, I was still walking beside him, but he suddenly turned into the Hôtel des Quatre Saisons, which stood on the road, nodded to me, and disappeared.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">On the way home I gradually realized that, even if I talked with him for two hours, I would learn decidedly nothing, because… I had nothing to ask him!</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Yes, of course, it was so! There was no way I could now formulate my question. All that day, Polina either walked in the park with the children and the nanny, or sat at home.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">She had long been avoiding the general and barely spoke to him, at any rate about anything serious. I had long noticed it. But, knowing the situation the general was in that day, I thought he couldn’t pass her by, that is, it was impossible for there not to be any important family discussions.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">Nevertheless, when, on returning to the hotel after my conversation with Mr. Astley, I met Polina and the children, her face reflected the most untroubled calm, as if all the family storms had passed by her alone.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">In response to my bow she nodded her head. I came to my room totally angry.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Of course, after the incident with the Wurmerhelms, I avoided talking with her and never once got together with her. In that I was partly showing off and posturing; but as time went on, real indignation seethed in me more and more. Even if she didn’t love me in the least, it still seemed wrong to trample on my feelings that way and receive my declarations with such contempt.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">She does know that I truly love her; she herself has allowed, has permitted me to speak that way with her! True, it began somehow strangely with us.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">Sometime long ago now, a good two months back, I began to notice that she wanted to make me her friend, a confidant, and she was even partly testing me. But for some reason it didn’t get going between us then; and instead it has remained in these present strange relations; that was why I began to speak that way with her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">But if she’s repulsed by my love, why not forbid me outright to speak of it? She doesn’t forbid me; she herself even occasionally initiated a conversation with me, and… of course, did it to make fun of me. I know for certain, I firmly noted it–it was a pleasure for her to listen to me and exacerbate me painfully, to stun me suddenly with a show of the greatest contempt and negligence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">And she knows that I can’t live without her. It’s three days now since the story with the baron, and I can no longer bear our She has a secret–that’s clear! Her conversation with grandmother pricked my heart painfully.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">A thousand times I’ve invited her to be frank with me, and she knew that I was actually ready to lay down my life for her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">But she always got off with near contempt, or, instead of the sacrifice of my life, which I had offered her, demanded escapades from me like that time with the baron! Isn’t it outrageous? Can it be that for her the whole world is in this Frenchman?</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">And Mr. Astley? But here the affair was becoming decidedly incomprehensible, and meanwhile–God, how I suffered! Having come home, in a fit of rage I seized a pen and scribbled the following: Polina Alexandrovna, I see clearly that the denouement has come, which will, of course, affect you as well.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">I repeat for the last time: do you need my life or not? If you need me I sealed this note and sent it with the floorboy, with orders that he put it directly into her hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">I didn’t expect an answer, but three minutes later the floorboy came back, saying that “the lady sends her greetings.” Sometime after six I was summoned to the general. He was in his study and dressed as if he was about to go out. His hat and stick lay on the sofa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">I fancied, as I came in, that he was standing in the middle of the room, his legs straddled, his head bowed, saying something aloud to himself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">But as soon as he saw me, he rushed to me all but with a shout, so that I involuntarily drew back and was about to run away; but he seized me by both hands and pulled me to the sofa; he sat down on the sofa himself, seated me directly opposite him in an armchair, and, without letting go of my hands, with trembling lips, with tears suddenly glistening on his eyelashes, said to me in a pleading voice: “Alexei Ivanovich, save me, save me, spare me!” For a long time I could understand nothing; he kept talking, talking, talking, and kept repeating: “Spare me, spare me!” I finally realized that he expected something like advice from me; or, better to say, abandoned by everybody, anguished and anxious, he had remembered me and summoned me in order to talk, talk, talk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">He had gone crazy, or at any rate was bewildered in the highest degree.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">He clasped his hands and was ready to throw himself on his knees before me to persuade me to–what do you think?–to go at once to Mlle Blanche and beg her, exhort her to return to him and marry him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“For pity’s sake, General,” I cried, “it may well be that Mlle Blanche hasn’t noticed me up to now! What can I do?” But it was useless to object: he didn’t understand what was said to him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">He began talking about grandmother as well, only it was terribly incoherent; he still stood by the notion of sending for the police. “With us, with us,” he began, suddenly boiling over with indignation, “in short, with us, in our wellorganized state, where authorities do exist, such old women would immediately be taken into custody!</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">Yes, my dear sir, yes,” he went on, suddenly lapsing into a scolding tone, jumping up and pacing the room, “you still don’t know that, my dear sir,” he turned to some imaginary dear sir in the corner, “so now you’ll learn… yes, sir… with us such old women get tied in a knot, yes, a knot, a knot, sir… oh, devil take it!” And he threw himself down on the sofa again, but a minute later, all but spluttering, breathless, he hastened to tell me that Mlle Blanche wouldn’t marry him because grandmother had come instead of a telegram, and it was now clear that he would get no inheritance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">He thought I still didn’t know any of it. I tried to mention des Grieux; he waved his hand: “Gone! Everything I own is mortgaged to him; I’m naked as a worm! That money you brought… that money–I don’t know how much is left, I think about seven hundred francs, and–enough, sir, that’s it, and beyond that I don’t know, I don’t know, sir!… ” “How are you going to pay for the hotel?” I cried in alarm, “and… then what?” He glanced around pensively, but didn’t seem to understand, and maybe hadn’t even heard me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">I tried to start talking about Polina Alexandrovna, about the children; he hurriedly answered, “Yes! yes!” but at once began talking about the prince again, about the fact that Blanche was now going off with him, and then… “and then… what am I to do, Alexei Ivanovich?” he suddenly turned to me. “I swear to God! What am I to do?–tell me, that’s really ungrateful!</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">isn’t it ungrateful?” Finally, he dissolved in a flood of tears. There was nothing to be done with a man like that; to leave him alone was also dangerous; something might happen to him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">However, I somehow got rid of him, but gave the nanny to know that she should look in on him often, and besides that I told the floorboy, a very sensible fellow, who for his part also promised me to keep an eye on him.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">I no sooner left the general than Potapych came to me with a summons from grandmother. It was eight o’clock, and she had just come back from the vauxhall after losing definitively. I went to her: the old woman was sitting in her chair, totally exhausted, and evidently sick.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">Marfa served her a cup of tea, which she almost forced her to drink. Grandmother’s voice and tone were markedly changed. “Good evening, dearest Alexei Ivanovich,” she said, inclining her head slowly and gravely, “forgive me for troubling you once more, forgive an old woman.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">I, my dear, left everything there, nearly a hundred thousand roubles.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">You were right not to go with me yesterday. I have no money now, not a penny. I don’t want to delay for a moment, I’ll leave at halfpast nine. I’ve sent to that Englishman of yours, Astley or whatever, and want to borrow three thousand francs from him for a week.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">You persuade him, so he doesn’t get some notion and say no. I’m still quite rich, my dear. I have three estates and two houses. And some money can be found, I didn’t take it all with me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">I say it so that he won’t have doubts of some sort… Ah, here he is! You can tell a good man when you see one.” Mr. Astley came hurrying at grandmother’s first summons.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">Without much reflection or talk, he at once counted out three thousand francs against a promissory note which grandmother proceeded to sign.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">The business concluded, he bowed and hurriedly left.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">“And now you go, too, Alexei Ivanovich. There’s a little more than an hour left–I want to lie down, my bones ache. Don’t judge me too harshly, fool that I am. Now I’ll never accuse young people of lightmindedness, and it would also be a sin now for me to accuse that unfortunate fellow, that general of yours.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">Even so I won’t give him any money, as he wants, because in my opinion he’s as foolish as they come, though I’m no smarter than he is, old fool that I am.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">Truly, God judges old age as well and punishes pride. Well, goodbye. Marfusha, lift me up.” I wished to see grandmother off, however. Besides, I was in some sort of expectation, I kept expecting that something was about to happen.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">I couldn’t sit in my room. I went out to the corridor several times, even went out for a moment to wander in the avenue.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">My letter to her had been clear and decisive, and the present catastrophe was, of course, definitive.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">In the hotel I heard of des Grieux’s departure. Finally, if she rejects me as a friend, maybe she won’t reject me as a servant. She does need me, at any rate to run errands; I’ll be useful, it can’t be otherwise!</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">By train time I ran to the station and got grandmother seated. They all settled in a special family car. “Thank you, dearie, for your disinterested concern,” she said at parting, “and tell Praskovya what I said to her yesterday–I’ll be waiting for her.” I went home.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">Passing by the general’s suite, I met the nanny and inquired about the general. “Him, dearie? He’s all right,” she answered glumly. I stepped in anyhow, but in the doorway to the study I stopped in decided amazement.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Mlle Blanche and the general were laughing their heads off over something. Having paused on the threshold of the general’s study, I decided not to go in and went away unnoticed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">Going up to my room and opening the door, I suddenly noticed some figure in the semidarkness, sitting on a chair in the corner by the window. It didn’t get up when I appeared.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">I quickly approached, looked, and–my breath was taken away: it was Polina!</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="14" name="CHAPTER XIV">
			<sentence num="1"> I CRIED OUT. “What is it?</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">What is it?” she asked strangely.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">She was pale and looked gloomy.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">“What do you mean, what?</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">You?</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">here, in my room?” “If I come, I come I lit a candle.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">She stood up, went to the table, and placed an unsealed letter before me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">“Read it,” she ordered. “This–this is des Grieux’s hand!” I cried, snatching the letter.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">My hands shook, and the lines leaped before my eyes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">I’ve forgotten the exact terms of the letter, but here it is, if not word for word, at least thought for thought.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">“Well, it’s all clear,” I said, turning to Polina, “not that you could have expected anything else,” I added indignantly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">“I wasn’t expecting anything,” she replied with apparent calm, but something seemed to tremble in her voice. “I resolved everything long ago; I read his mind and knew what he thought.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">He thought that I was seeking… that I’d insist… ” She stopped and, without finishing, bit her lip and fell silent.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">“I purposely doubled my contempt for him,” she began again, “I waited for what he would do. If the telegram about the inheritance had come, I would have flung my idiot stepfather’s debt at him and chased him away!</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">He’s been hateful to me for a long, long time. Oh, this was not the man of before, a thousand times not, and now, and now!… Oh, what happiness it would be now to fling that fifty thousand in his mean face, and spit… and smear it around!” “But the paper–that mortgage for fifty thousand he returned–isn’t it with the general?</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">Take it and give it to des Grieux.” “Oh, that’s not it! That’s not it!” “Yes, true, that’s not it! And what use is the general now? But what about grandmother?” I cried suddenly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">Polina looked at me somehow distractedly and impatiently. “Why grandmother?” Polina said with vexation.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">“I can’t go to her… And I don’t want to ask anyone’s forgiveness,” she added irritably. “What’s to be done, then?” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">“And how, how could you love des Grieux! Oh, the scoundrel, the scoundrel! Well, if you like, I’ll kill him in a duel!</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">Where is he now?” “He’s in Frankfurt and will be there for three days.” “One word from you, and I’ll go tomorrow by the first train,” I said in some sort of stupid enthusiasm.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">She laughed. “Why, he might just say: first return the fifty thousand francs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">And why would he fight?… What nonsense!” “But where, then, where can we get these fifty thousand francs?” I repeated, grinding my teeth, as if one could just suddenly pick them up off the floor.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">“Listen: Mr. Astley?” I asked, turning to her with the beginnings of some strange idea.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">Her eyes flashed. “What, do It seems at that moment her head began spinning from agitation, and she suddenly sat down on the sofa as if in exhaustion.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">It was like being struck by lightning: I stood there and couldn’t believe my eyes, couldn’t believe my ears!</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">So it meant she loved me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">She came A wild thought flashed in my head. “Polina! Give me just one hour!</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">Wait here for only one hour and… I’ll come back!</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">It’s… it’s necessary!</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">You’ll see! Stay here, stay here!” And I ran out of the room without responding to her astonished, questioning look; she called out something after me, but I didn’t go back.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">Yes, sometimes the wildest thought, the seemingly most impossible thought, gets so firmly settled in your head that you finally take it for something feasible… Moreover, if the idea is combined with a strong, passionate desire, you might one day take it, finally, for something fatal, inevitable, predestined, for something that can no longer not be and not happen!</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">Maybe there’s also something else, some combination of presentiments, some extraordinary effort of will, a selfintoxication by your own fantasy, or whatever else–I don’t know; but on that evening (which I will never forget as long as I live) a miraculous event took place.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">Though it is perfectly justified arithmetically, nonetheless for me it is still miraculous.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">And why, why did this certainty lodge itself so deeply and firmly in me then, and now so long ago?</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">I surely must have thought of it, I repeat to you, not as an event that might happen among others (and therefore also might not happen), but as something that simply could not fail to happen!</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">It was a quarterpast ten; I entered the vauxhall in such firm hopes and at the same time in such excitement as I had never experienced before.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">There were still enough people in the gaming rooms, though twice less than in the morning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">After ten o’clock, those left around the gaming tables are the real, desperate gamblers, for whom nothing exists at the spa except roulette, who come for the sake of it alone, who give poor notice to what happens around them, and are interested in nothing else during the whole season, but only play from morning till night, and would be ready, perhaps, to play all night till dawn, if it were possible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">And they always go away grudgingly when the roulette closes at midnight.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">And when, around midnight, before closing the roulette, the head croupier announces: “ “ I won–and again staked everything: the previous money and the winnings.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">“ I was as if in a fever and pushed this whole pile of money onto red–and suddenly came to my senses! And for the only time that whole evening, in all that playing, fear sent a chill over me and came back as a trembling in my hands and legs. With terror I sensed and instantly realized what it meant for me now to lose! My whole life was at stake!</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">“ Then, I remember, I staked two thousand florins on the twelve middle numbers again and lost; I staked my gold and eighty friedrichs d’or and lost. Rage came over me: I seized the last remaining two thousand florins and staked them on the twelve first numbers–just so, in case, like that, without calculation!</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">However, there was one moment of expectation, perhaps similar in impression to that experienced by Mme Blanchard, in Paris, as she fell to the ground from a hotair balloon.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">{13} “ It came up black. Here I no longer remember either my reckoning or the order of my stakes. I only remember, as in a dream, that it seems I won sixteen thousand florins; then, in three unlucky turns, I blew twelve of them; then I pushed the remaining four thousand onto I think no more than half an hour had gone by since my arrival.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">Suddenly the croupier informed me that I had won thirty thousand florins, and since the bank could not answer for more at one time, it meant that the roulette would close till the next morning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">I grabbed all my gold, poured it into my pockets, grabbed all the banknotes, and at once moved to another table, in another room, where there was another roulette; a whole crowd flocked after me; a place was cleared for me at once, and I began staking again, anyhow and without calculating.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">I have no idea what saved me! Occasionally, however, calculation began to flash in my head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">I would latch on to certain numbers and choices, but soon abandoned them and staked again almost unawares. I must have been very distracted; I remember that the croupiers corrected my play several times.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">I made bad mistakes. My temples were damp with sweat, and my hands shook.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">Little Poles ran up to me with their services, but I didn’t listen to anyone. My luck held out!</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">Suddenly loud talk and laughter arose around me. “Bravo, bravo!” everyone cried, some even clapped their hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">I won thirty thousand florins here as well, breaking the bank, which was closed till the next day!</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">“Leave, leave,” someone’s voice whispered to me on my right. It was some Frankfurt Jew; he had been standing next to me all the while and, it seems, had occasionally helped me to play.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">“For God’s sake, leave,” another voice whispered in my left ear.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">I glanced up fleetingly. It was a quite modestly and decently dressed lady of about thirty, with a sickly pale, weary face, but even now recalling her wonderful former beauty.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">At that moment I was stuffing my pockets with banknotes, which I just crumpled up, and gathering the gold that was left on the table.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">Seizing the last roll of fifty friedrichs d’or, I managed, quite unnoticed, to put it into the pale lady’s hand; I wanted terribly to do that then, and I remember her slender, thin fingers pressed my hand hard as a sign of warmest gratitude.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">All this took only a moment. Having gathered up everything, I quickly went on to the  It actually seemed that fate was urging me on.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">This time, as if on purpose, a certain circumstance occurred, which, however, is repeated rather often in gambling. Luck attaches itself, for instance, to red, and doesn’t leave it for ten, even fifteen times in a row. I had heard two days earlier that, a week before, red had come up twentytwo times in a row; no one even remembered such a thing happening at roulette, and it was retold with amazement.</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">Naturally, everyone abandoned red at once, and after ten times, for instance, almost no one dared to stake on it. But no experienced gambler would have staked on black then as opposed to red.</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">An experienced gambler knows what this “whim of chance” means. For instance, it would seem that, after sixteen reds, the seventeenth is bound to be black.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">Novices fall upon it in crowds, doubling and tripling their stakes, and lose terribly. But I, by some strange whim, noticing that red had come up seven times in a row, deliberately latched on to it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">I’m convinced that it was half vanity; I wanted to astonish the spectators with an insane risk, and–oh, strange feeling–I distinctly remember that suddenly, indeed without any challenge to my vanity, I was overcome by a terrible thirst for risk.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Maybe, having gone through so many sensations, my soul was not sated but only exacerbated by them, and demanded more sensations, ever stronger and stronger, to the point of utter exhaustion. And, I’m truly not lying, if the rules of the game had allowed me to stake fifty thousand florins at once, I would certainly have staked them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Around me they cried that it was insane, that red had already come up fourteen times!</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">“ I suddenly came to my senses. What? I had won a hundred thousand florins that evening! What did I need more for?</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">I fell upon the banknotes, crumpled them into my pocket without counting, raked up all my gold, all the rolls, and ran out of the vauxhall.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">Around me everyone laughed as I passed through the rooms, looking at my bulging pockets and my uneven gait owing to the weight of the gold.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">I think it weighed over seventeen pounds.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">Several hands reached out to me; I gave money away by the handful, as much as I got hold of.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">Two Jews stopped me at the exit. “You’re bold! You’re very bold!” they said to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">“But leave tomorrow morning without fail, otherwise you’ll lose it all… ” I didn’t listen to them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">The avenue was so dark that I couldn’t see my own hand. It was about a quarter of a mile to the hotel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">I had never been afraid of thieves or robbers, even when I was little; I didn’t think of them now either.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">However, I don’t remember what I thought about on the way; there were no thoughts. My only sensation was of some terrible pleasure–luck, victory, power–I don’t know how to express it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">The image of Polina flashed before me as well; I remembered and was conscious that I was going to her, that I would presently be together with her and would be telling her, showing her… but I barely remembered what she had said to me earlier, and why I had gone, and all those recent sensations, which had been there an hour and a half ago, now seemed to me something long past, corrected, outdated–of which we would make no further mention, because now everything would start anew.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">Almost at the end of the avenue fear suddenly came upon me: “What if I’m murdered and robbed right now!” With each step, my fear redoubled.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">I nearly ran. Suddenly at the end of the avenue our hotel shone all at once, lit up by countless lights–thank God: home!</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">I ran up to my floor and quickly opened the door.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">Polina was there, sitting on my sofa in front of a lighted candle, her arms crossed. She looked at me in amazement, and I certainly was a strange sight at that moment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">I stopped before her and began flinging my whole pile of money on the table.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="15" name="CHAPTER XV">
			<sentence num="1"> I REMEMBER SHE LOOKED terribly intently into my face, but without moving, without even changing her position.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">“I won two hundred thousand francs,” I cried, flinging down my last roll.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">The enormous pile of banknotes and rolls of gold covered the whole table, and I couldn’t take my eyes off it; at moments I completely forgot about Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">Now I’d begin putting all those heaps of banknotes in order, stacking them together, now I’d gather the gold into one common heap; then I’d abandon it all and begin pacing the room in quick strides, lapsing into thought; then I’d suddenly go up to the table and begin counting the money again.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">Suddenly, as if coming to my senses, I rushed to the door and quickly locked it, turning the key twice.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">Then I stopped, pondering, before my little suitcase.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">“Shouldn’t I put it in the suitcase till tomorrow?” I asked, suddenly turning to Polina, and I suddenly remembered about her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">She went on sitting without stirring, in the same place, but was watching me intently.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">The expression on her face was somehow strange; I didn’t like that expression!</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">I wouldn’t be mistaken if I said there was hatred in it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">I quickly went over to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">“Polina, here’s twentyfive thousand florins–that’s fifty thousand francs, even more.</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Take it, fling it in his face tomorrow.” She didn’t answer me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">“If you like, I’ll take it myself, early in the morning.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Shall I?” She suddenly began to laugh.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">She laughed for a long time.</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">I looked at her with astonishment and sorrowful feeling.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">This laughter was very much like her recent, frequent, mocking laughter at me, which always came at the time of my most passionate declarations.</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">Finally, she stopped and frowned; she looked me over sternly from under her eyebrows.</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">“I won’t take your money,” she said contemptuously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">“How’s that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">What’s wrong?” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">“Why, Polina?” “I don’t take money for nothing.” “I’m offering it to you as a friend; I’m offering you my life.” She looked at me with a long, searching gaze, as if she wanted to pierce me through.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">“You’re paying too much,” she said, smiling, “des Grieux’s mistress isn’t worth fifty thousand francs.” “Polina, how can you speak to me like that!” I cried in reproach.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">“Am I des Grieux?” “I hate you!</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">Yes… yes!… I dislike you more than des Grieux,” she cried, suddenly flashing her eyes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">Here she suddenly covered her face with her hands and went into hysterics.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">I rushed to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">I realized that something had happened to her in my absence.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">It was as if she was not at all in her right mind.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">“Buy me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">You want to?</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">you want to? for fifty thousand francs, like des Grieux?” she burst out with convulsive sobs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">I embraced her, kissed her hands, her feet, fell on my knees before her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">Her hysterics were passing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">She put both hands on my shoulders and studied me intently. It seemed as if she wanted to read something in my face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">She listened to me, but apparently without hearing what I said to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">Some sort of care and pensiveness appeared in her face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">I feared for her; it decidedly seemed to me that her mind was becoming deranged.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">She would suddenly begin to draw me gently to her; a trustful smile would wander over her face; then she would suddenly push me away, and again start peering at me with a darkened look.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">Suddenly she rushed to embrace me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">“You do love me, don’t you?” she said.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“Why, you wanted… you wanted to fight with the baron over me!” And she suddenly burst out laughing–as if something funny and dear had suddenly flashed in her memory.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">She wept and laughed at the same time.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">Well, what was I to do?</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">I was as if in a fever myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">I remember she began saying something to me, but I could understand almost nothing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">It was some kind of raving, some kind of prattle–as if she wanted to tell me something quickly–raving interrupted now and then by the merriest laughter, which began to frighten me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">“No, no, you’re a dear, a dear!” she repeated.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">“You’re my faithful one!” and she again put her hands on my shoulders, again peered at me and went on repeating: “You love me… love me… will you love me?” I couldn’t take my eyes off her; I had never yet seen her in these fits of tenderness and love; true, it was, of course, raving, but… noticing my passionate look, she would suddenly begin to smile slyly; for no reason at all she would start talking about Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">However, she mentioned Mr. Astley constantly (especially earlier, when she had tried to tell me something), but precisely what it was, I couldn’t grasp; it seemed she even laughed at him; she constantly repeated that he was waiting… and did I know that he was certainly standing under the window now?</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">“Yes, yes, under the window–well, open it, look, look, he’s here, here!” She pushed me towards the window, but as soon as I made as if to go to it, she dissolved in laughter, and I stayed by her, and she rushed to embrace me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">“So we’re leaving?</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">Aren’t we leaving tomorrow?” suddenly came anxiously to her head.</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">“Well… ”(and she fell to thinking), “well, will we catch up with grandmother, do you think?</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">What do you think she’ll say when we catch up with her and she sees us?</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">And Mr. Astley?… Well, that one won’t jump off the Schlangenberg, do you think?” (She laughed loudly.)</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">“Well, listen: do you know where he’s going next summer?</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">He wants to go to the North Pole for scientific research, and he invited me to go with him, ha, ha, ha!</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">He says that without the Europeans we Russians don’t know anything and can’t do anything… But he’s also kind!</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">You know, he excuses the ‘general’; he says that Blanche… that passion–well, I don’t know, I don’t know,” she suddenly repeated as if wandering and at a loss.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">“Poor things, I’m so sorry for them and for grandmother… No, listen, listen, who are you to go killing des Grieux?</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">And did you really and truly think you’d kill him?</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Oh, silly boy!</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">Could you possibly think I’d let you fight with des Grieux?</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">And you wouldn’t kill the baron either,” she added, suddenly bursting into laughter.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">“Oh, how ridiculous you were then with the baron; I watched the two of you from my bench; and how reluctant you were to go then, when I sent you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">How I laughed then, how I laughed,” she added, laughing loudly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">And again she suddenly kissed me and embraced me, again she pressed her face to mine passionately and tenderly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">I no longer thought or heard anything.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">My head was spinning… I think it was about seven o’clock in the morning when I came to my senses; the sun was shining into the room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">Polina was sitting next to me and looking around strangely, as if coming out of some darkness and collecting her memories.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">She also had only just woken up and gazed intently at the table and the money.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">My head was heavy and ached.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">I was about to take Polina’s hand; she suddenly pushed me away and jumped up from the sofa.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">The beginning day was overcast; it had rained before dawn.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">She went to the window, opened it, thrust out her head and chest, and, propping herself on her hands, her elbows resting on the windowsill, stayed that way for about three minutes, without turning to me or listening to what I was saying to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">With fear it came to my head: what will come now and how will it end?</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">Suddenly she got up from the window, went over to the table, and, looking at me with an expression of boundless hatred, her lips trembling with anger, said to me: “Well, now give me my fifty thousand francs!” “Again, again, Polina!” I tried to begin.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">“Or have you changed your mind?</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">Ha, ha, ha!</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">Maybe you’re sorry now?” The twentyfive thousand florins, already counted out last night, were lying on the table.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">I took them and gave them to her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">“So it’s mine now?</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">Is it? Is it?” she asked me spitefully, holding the money in her hands.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">“But it has always been yours,” I said.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">“Well, then, here’s your fifty thousand francs!” She swung and sent them flying at me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">The wad struck me painfully in the face and scattered over the floor.</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">Having done that, Polina ran out of the room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">I know, of course, she was not in her right mind at that moment, though I don’t understand this temporary madness.</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">True, even now, a month later, she’s still unwell.</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">What, however, was the cause of this condition and, above all, of this escapade?</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">Injured pride?</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">Despair over the fact that she had even ventured to come to me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">Did I look to her as if I was glorying in my success and indeed, just like des Grieux, wanted to get rid of her by giving her fifty thousand francs?</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">But that wasn’t so, I know it by my own conscience.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">I think that part of the blame here lay in her vanity: vanity prompted her not to believe me and to insult me, though all this may have presented itself to her quite vaguely.</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">In that case, of course, I answered for des Grieux, and was to blame, maybe, without much blame.</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">True, all this was only delirium; it’s also true that I knew she was delirious, and… paid no attention to that circumstance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">Maybe now she can’t forgive me for it?</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">Yes, but that’s now; but then, then?</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">Her delirium and illness were not so strong that she totally forgot what she was doing when she came to me with des Grieux’s letter?</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">So she knew what she was doing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">Carelessly, hastily, I stuffed all my paper money and my whole heap of gold into the bed, covered it, and left some ten minutes after Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">I was sure she had run home, and wanted to get to their suite quietly and ask the nanny in the front room about the young lady’s health.</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">What was my amazement when, meeting the nanny on the stairs, I learned that Polina had not returned home yet and that the nanny herself was coming to my room to fetch her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">“Just now,” I said to her, “she left me only just now, some ten minutes ago, where could she have gone?” The nanny looked at me reproachfully.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">And meanwhile a whole story had come out, which had already spread through the hotel.</sentence>
			<sentence num="109">In the porter’s lodge and at the manager’s it was whispered that, at six o’clock in the morning, the It was still early; Mr. Astley was not receiving anyone; learning that it was I, he came out to me in the corridor and stood before me, silently aiming his tinny gaze at me, waiting for what I was going to say.</sentence>
			<sentence num="110">I inquired at once about Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="111">“She’s ill,” Mr. Astley replied, looking at me pointblank as before and not taking his eyes off me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="112">“So she’s really here with you?” “Oh, yes, with me.” “So, then, you… you intend to keep her with you?” “Oh, yes, I do.” “Mr.</sentence>
			<sentence num="113">Astley, this will cause a scandal; this is impossible.</sentence>
			<sentence num="114">Besides, she’s quite ill; maybe you haven’t noticed?” “Oh, yes, I have, and I’ve already told you she’s ill.</sentence>
			<sentence num="115">If she weren’t ill, she wouldn’t have spent the night with you.” “So you know that, too?” “I know that.</sentence>
			<sentence num="116">She was on her way here yesterday, and I would have taken her to my female relation, but since she was ill, she went to you by mistake.” “Imagine that!</sentence>
			<sentence num="117">Well, I congratulate you, Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="118">By the way, you’ve given me an idea: didn’t you spend the whole night standing under the window?</sentence>
			<sentence num="119">Miss Polina kept telling me all night to open the window and see whether you were standing there, and she laughed terribly.” “Really?</sentence>
			<sentence num="120">No, I wasn’t standing under the window; but I waited in the corridor and walked about.” “But she needs to be treated, Mr. Astley.” “Oh, yes, I’ve already sent for a doctor, and if she dies, you will give me an accounting for her death.” I was amazed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="121">“For pity’s sake, Mr. Astley, what is it you want?” “Is it true that you won two hundred thousand thalers yesterday?” “Only one hundred thousand florins in all.” “Well, you see!</sentence>
			<sentence num="122">So, then, go to Paris this morning.” “What for?” “All Russians go to Paris when they have money,” Mr. Astley explained in a voice and tone as if he was reading it from a book.</sentence>
			<sentence num="123">“What will I do in Paris now, in the summer?</sentence>
			<sentence num="124">I love her, Mr. Astley!</sentence>
			<sentence num="125">You know it yourself.” “Really?</sentence>
			<sentence num="126">I’m convinced that you don’t.</sentence>
			<sentence num="127">Besides, if you stay here, you’re certain to lose everything, and you won’t have the money to go to Paris.</sentence>
			<sentence num="128">But goodbye, I’m perfectly convinced that you’ll go to Paris today.” “Very well, goodbye, only I won’t go to Paris.</sentence>
			<sentence num="129">Think, Mr. Astley, about how it will be for us now.</sentence>
			<sentence num="130">In short, the general… and now what’s happend with Miss Polina–why, it will get all over town.” “Yes, all over town.</sentence>
			<sentence num="131">The general, I think, doesn’t think about it and couldn’t care less.</sentence>
			<sentence num="132">Besides, Miss Polina is fully entitled to live wherever she likes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="133">As for this family, it would be correct to say that this family no longer exists.” I walked along and chuckled at this Englishman’s strange certainty that I would go to Paris.</sentence>
			<sentence num="134">“Anyhow he wants to shoot me in a duel,” I thought, “if Mlle Polina dies–there’s another business!” I swear I felt sorry for Polina, but, strangely, since the moment I touched the gaming table the night before and began to rake in wads of money, it was as if my love moved into the background.</sentence>
			<sentence num="135">I say that now; but at the time I still hadn’t noted it all clearly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="136">Can it be that I’m really a gambler, can it be that I indeed… loved Polina so strangely?</sentence>
			<sentence num="137">No, I love her even now, by God!</sentence>
			<sentence num="138">And at that moment, when I left Mr. Astley and walked home, I sincerely suffered and blamed myself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="139">But… but here I got involved in an extremely strange and stupid story.</sentence>
			<sentence num="140">I was hurrying to the general’s when a door suddenly opened near their suite and someone called out to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="141">It was Mme They had a small tworoom suite. I could hear the laughter and cries of Mlle Blanche from the bedroom.</sentence>
			<sentence num="142">She was getting up.</sentence>
			<sentence num="143">“ “I did win,” I answered, laughing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="144">“How much?” “A hundred thousand florins.” “ I went into her room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="145">She was lying under a pink satin spread, from which her swarthy, healthy, astonishing shoulders protruded–shoulders such as can only be seen in a dream–negligently covered by a batiste nightgown trimmed with the whitest lace, which went wonderfully with her swarthy skin.</sentence>
			<sentence num="146">“ “ “You see, “Now?” “In half an hour.” Indeed, everything was packed. All her suitcases and things were standing ready. Coffee had been served long ago.</sentence>
			<sentence num="147">“ She stuck out a really delightful little foot, swarthy, small, not misshapen, like almost all those little feet that look so cute in shoes.</sentence>
			<sentence num="148">I laughed and began to pull a silk stocking onto it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="149">Mlle Blanche meanwhile sat on the bed and chattered.</sentence>
			<sentence num="150">“ “Wait, so I give you fifty thousand francs, and what am I left with?” “ “What, all in two months?” “What? So it frightens you? At that moment I was putting a stocking on her other foot, but I couldn’t help myself and kissed it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="151">She pulled it back and began flicking me in the face with her toe.</sentence>
			<sentence num="152">Finally, she drove me out altogether. “ Returning home, I was already as if in a whirl.</sentence>
			<sentence num="153">What, then, was it my fault that Mlle Polina had thrown the whole wad in my face and already yesterday had preferred Mr. Astley to me?</sentence>
			<sentence num="154">Some stray banknotes still lay on the floor; I picked them up. At that moment the door opened and the manager himself (who wouldn’t even look at me before) came with an invitation: wouldn’t I like to move downstairs to an excellent suite in which Count V. had just been staying?</sentence>
			<sentence num="155">I stood and thought a moment. “The bill!” I cried.</sentence>
			<sentence num="156">“I’m leaving right now, in ten minutes.” “If it’s Paris, let it be Paris,” I thought to myself, “it must have been written down at my birth!” A quarter of an hour later the three of us were indeed sitting in a family compartment: myself, Mlle Blanche, and Mme “But what is it to you?</sentence>
			<sentence num="157">How stupid you are!</sentence>
			<sentence num="158">oh, how stupid!” cried Blanche, interrupting her laughter and beginning to scold me seriously.</sentence>
			<sentence num="159">“Well, yes, yes, we’ll go through your two hundred thousand francs, but to make up for it, “And the general?” I asked her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="160">“And the general, as you know yourself, goes to fetch me a bouquet every day at this hour. Today I purposely told him to find the rarest flowers. The poor thing will come back, and the bird will have flown. He’ll fly after us, you’ll see.</sentence>
			<sentence num="161">Ha, ha, ha!</sentence>
			<sentence num="162">I’ll be very glad. He’ll be useful to me in Paris; here Mr. Astley will pay for him… ” And so it was that I left for Paris then.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="16" name="CHAPTER XVI">
			<sentence num="1"> WHAT SHALL I SAY about Paris?</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">It was all, of course, both delirium and foolery.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">I lived in Paris for only a little more than three weeks, and in that time my hundred thousand francs were completely finished.</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">I’m speaking of only a hundred thousand; the remaining hundred thousand I gave to Mlle Blanche in straight cash–fifty thousand in Frankfurt, and three days later in Paris I handed her the other fifty thousand francs in a promissory note, for which, however, she took the money from me a week later, “ “What do you need money for?” she said occasionally with a most artless look, and I didn’t argue with her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">Instead, she decorated her apartment very, very nicely on this money, and later when she moved me to the new place, she said, as she was showing me the rooms: “See what can be done, with calculation and taste, on the scantiest means.” This scantiness added up, however, to exactly fifty thousand francs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">The other fifty thousand she spent on a carriage and horses, and besides that we threw two balls, that is, two evening parties, to which Hortense, and Lisette, and Cléopatre came–women remarkable in many, many respects, and even far from bad.</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">At these two parties I was forced to play the utterly stupid role of host, to meet and entertain some rich and extremely dull merchants, impossibly ignorant and shameless army lieutenants of various sorts, and pathetic little authors and magazine midges, who arrived in fashionable tailcoats, strawcolored gloves, and with a vanity and conceit of dimensions inconceivable even in Petersburg–which is saying a lot.</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">They even ventured to make fun of me, but I got drunk on champagne and lay about in the back room.</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">All this was loathsome to me in the highest degree.</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">“ “Well, so, Bibi, you’re not angry?” she came up to me. “Nooo!</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">How boooring!” I said, moving her away with my hand, but this made her so curious that she at once sat down beside me: “You see, if I decided to pay so much, it’s because they were a good deal.</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">They can be sold again for twenty thousand francs.” “I believe you, I believe you; they’re splendid horses; and now you’ve got a nice turnout; it will be useful; well, and enough.” “So you’re not angry?” “At what?</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">It’s smart of you to stock up on a few things you need.</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">It will all be of use later.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">I see you really have to put yourself on such a footing, otherwise you’ll never make a million.</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">Here our hundred thousand francs is only a beginning, a drop in the ocean.” Blanche, who least of all expected such talk from me (instead of shouts and reproaches!</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">), looked as if she’d fallen from the sky.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">“So you… so that’s how you are!</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">“Who cares, the quicker the better!” “ “ “ “No, lies!</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">And with Albert, that swarthy little officer–as if I didn’t see it last time?” “ “No, lies, lies; and what do you think, that I’m angry?</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">I spit on it; “So you’re not angry about that either?</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">And, indeed, since then it was even as if she really did become attached to me, even in a friendly way, and so we spent our last ten days.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">The promised “stars” I didn’t see; but in some respects she really kept her word.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">Moreover, she got me acquainted with Hortense, who was even all too remarkable a woman in her own way and in our circle was known as However, there’s no point expanding on it; all this could make up a special story, with a special coloring, which I don’t want to put into this story.</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">The thing is that I wished with all my might that it would all be over soon.</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">But our hundred thousand francs lasted, as I’ve already said, for almost a month–at which I was genuinely surprised: at least eighty thousand of this money Blanche spent buying things for herself, and we lived on no more than twenty thousand francs, and even so it was enough.</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">Blanche, who towards the end was even almost candid with me (at least in certain things she didn’t lie to me), confessed that at least the debts she had had to incur wouldn’t fall on me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">“I didn’t give you any bills or promissory notes to sign,” she said to me, “because I felt sorry for you; another woman would certainly have done that and packed you off to prison.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">You see, you see how I’ve loved you and how kind I am!</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">This damned wedding alone is going to cost me quite a bit!” We did indeed have a wedding.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">It took place at the very end of our month, and I suppose the last dregs of my hundred thousand francs went on it; with that the affair ended, that is, with that our month ended, after which I was formally dismissed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">It happened like this: a week after we installed ourselves in Paris, the general came.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">He came straight to Blanche and from the very first visit all but stayed with us.</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">True, he had his own little apartment somewhere. Blanche greeted him joyfully, with shrieks and loud laughter, and even rushed to embrace him; as things turned out, she herself wouldn’t let him go, and he had to follow her everywhere: to the boulevards, and for carriage rides, and to the theater, and to see acquaintances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">The general was still fit for this employment; he was rather stately and respectable–almost tall, with dyed sidewhiskers and enormous mustaches (he served formerly in the cuirassiers), with a distinguished though somewhat flabby face.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">His manners were excellent, he wore a tailcoat very smartly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">In Paris he started wearing his decorations.</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">With such a man, to stroll down the boulevard was not only possible, but, if one may put it so, even As soon as he appeared at our place, Blanche at once began acting as his advocate before me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">She even waxed eloquent. She reminded me that she had been unfaithful to the general because of me, that she had almost been his fiancée, had given him her word; that because of her he had abandoned his family, and that, finally, I worked for him and should be sensible of that, and–shame on me… I kept silent, and she rattled on terribly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">Finally, I burst out laughing, and the matter ended there, that is, at first she thought I was a fool, but towards the end she arrived at the notion that I was a very good and agreeable man.</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">In short, I had the luck, towards the end, decidedly to earn the full good favor of this worthy girl.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">(However, Blanche was in fact a most kind girl–only in her own way, of course; I didn’t appreciate her at first.)</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">“You’re an intelligent and kind man,” she used to say to me towards the end, “and… and… it’s too bad you’re such a fool!</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">You’ll never, never be rich!” “ I saw that things were coming along between them, but kept silent as usual.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">Blanche was the first to announce it to me: this was exactly a week before we parted.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">“ “Well, but if he begins to get jealous, demands… God knows what–you understand?” “Oh, no, “Well, so marry him… ” The wedding was quiet and familial, with no great pomp. Among those invited were Albert and a few close acquaintances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">Hortense, Cléopatre, and the rest were decidedly excluded.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">The groom was exceedingly concerned with his position. Blanche herself tied his necktie, pomaded him, and in his tailcoat and white waistcoat he looked “ “I must behave quite differently now,” she said to me with extreme seriousness, “ Finally we parted, and Blanche, that silly Blanche, even became tearful, saying goodbye to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">“ I still have about five hundred francs left; besides, I have a magnificent watch worth a thousand francs, diamond cuff links and the like, so I may still last a rather long time without worrying about anything.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">I’ve purposely lodged myself in this little town in order to pull myself together, but I’m mainly waiting for Mr. Astley. I’ve learned for certain that he’ll be passing through and will stop here for a day on business.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">I’ll find out about everything… and then–then go straight to Homburg. I won’t go to Roulettenburg, or not until next year.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">Indeed, they say it bodes ill to try your luck twice in a row at one and the same table, and Homburg is also where the real gambling is.</sentence>
		</chapter>
		<chapter num="17" name="CHAPTER XVII">
			<sentence num="1"> IT’S A YEAR AND eight months since I’ve looked at these notes, and only now, out of anguish and grief, has it occurred to me to divert myself and by chance read through them.</sentence>
			<sentence num="2">So I left off then on the point of going to Homburg.</sentence>
			<sentence num="3">God!</sentence>
			<sentence num="4">with what a–comparatively speaking–light heart I wrote those last lines then!</sentence>
			<sentence num="5">That is, not really with a light heart–but with what selfassurance, with what unshakable hopes!</sentence>
			<sentence num="6">Did I at least have some doubts of myself?</sentence>
			<sentence num="7">And here over a year and a half has gone by, and in my opinion I’m much worse than a beggar!</sentence>
			<sentence num="8">What’s a beggar!</sentence>
			<sentence num="9">Spit on beggary!</sentence>
			<sentence num="10">I’ve simply ruined myself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="11">However, there’s hardly anything that compares to it, and there’s no point in reading moral lessons to myself!</sentence>
			<sentence num="12">Nothing could be more absurd than moral lessons at such a moment!</sentence>
			<sentence num="13">Oh, selfsatisfied people: with what proud selfsatisfaction such babblers are ready to utter their pronouncements!</sentence>
			<sentence num="14">If they only knew to what degree I myself understand all the loathsomeness of my present condition, they wouldn’t have the heart to teach me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="15">Well, what, what new thing can they say to me that I don’t know myself?</sentence>
			<sentence num="16">And is that the point?</sentence>
			<sentence num="17">The point here is that–one turn of the wheel, and everything changes, and these same moralizers will be the first (I’m sure of it) to come with friendly jokes to congratulate me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="18">And they won’t all turn away from me as they do now. Spit on them all!</sentence>
			<sentence num="19">What am I now?</sentence>
			<sentence num="20">I actually went to Homburg then, but… later I was in Roulettenburg again, I was in Spa as well, I was even in Baden, where I went as the valet of the councillor Hintze, a scoundrel and my former master here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="21">Yes, I was also a lackey, for five whole months!</sentence>
			<sentence num="22">That happened right after prison.</sentence>
			<sentence num="23">(I got to prison in Roulettenburg for a debt I incurred here.</sentence>
			<sentence num="24">An unknown person bought me out–who was it? Mr. Astley? Polina?</sentence>
			<sentence num="25">I don’t know, but the debt was paid, two hundred thalers in all, and I was released.)</sentence>
			<sentence num="26">Where was I to go?</sentence>
			<sentence num="27">I went to work for this Hintze.</sentence>
			<sentence num="28">He’s a young and flighty man, likes to be lazy, and I can speak and write in three languages.</sentence>
			<sentence num="29">I began working for him as some sort of secretary, for thirty guldens a month; but I ended in real lackeydom with him: he didn’t have the means to keep a secretary, and he lowered my salary; since I had nowhere to go, I stayed–and thus turned myself into a lackey. I ate little and drank little while with him, and that way I saved seventy guldens in five months.</sentence>
			<sentence num="30">One evening in Baden, I announced to him that I wished to part with him; that same evening I went to play roulette.</sentence>
			<sentence num="31">Oh, how my heart throbbed! No, it wasn’t money that was dear to me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="32">My only wish then was that the next day all those Hintzes, all those hotel managers, all those magnificent Baden ladies–that they would all be talking about me, telling my story, astonished at me, praising me, and bowing before my new winnings.</sentence>
			<sentence num="33">That was all childish dreams and concerns, but… who knows, maybe I’d meet Polina, too, and tell her, and she’d see that I was above all these absurd jolts of fate… Oh, it’s not money that’s dear to me!</sentence>
			<sentence num="34">I’m sure I would have frittered it all away on some Blanche again and driven around Paris for three weeks with my own pair of horses worth sixteen thousand francs.</sentence>
			<sentence num="35">I know for certain that I’m not stingy: I even think I’m a spendthrift–and yet, even so, with what trepidation, with what a sinking heart I listen to the cry of the croupier: Oh, that evening when I carried my seventy guldens to the gaming table was also remarkable.</sentence>
			<sentence num="36">I began with ten guldens, and again with I took a room, locked myself in, and sat till three o’clock counting my money. The next morning I woke up a lackey no more. I decided that same day to leave for Homburg: there I had never served as a lackey or sat in prison. Half an hour before the train, I went to make two stakes, no more, and lost fifteen hundred florins.</sentence>
			<sentence num="37">However, I still moved to Homburg, and it’s a month now that I’ve been here… I live, of course, in constant anxiety, play for the smallest stakes, and am waiting for something, I calculate, I stand for whole days at the gaming table and “So you’re here!</sentence>
			<sentence num="38">I just thought I’d meet you,” he said to me.</sentence>
			<sentence num="39">“Don’t bother telling me: I know, I know everything; your whole life for the past year and eight months is known to me.” “Hah!</sentence>
			<sentence num="40">see how you keep track of old friends!” I replied. “It’s to your credit that you don’t forget… Wait, though, that gives me an idea–was it you who bought me out of the Roulettenburg prison, where I was sent for a debt of two hundred guldens? Some unknown person bought me out.” “No, oh, no!</sentence>
			<sentence num="41">I didn’t buy you out of the Roulettenburg prison, where you were sent for a debt of two hundred guldens, but I knew you had been sent to prison for a debt of two hundred guldens.” “So all the same you know who bought me out.” “Oh, no, I can’t say as I know who bought you out.” “Strange; our Russians don’t know me, and the Russians here probably wouldn’t buy anyone out; it’s there in Russia that Orthodox people buy out their own.</sentence>
			<sentence num="42">So I thought it might have been some odd Englishman, out of eccentricity.” Mr. Astley listened to me with some astonishment.</sentence>
			<sentence num="43">It seems he expected to find me crestfallen and crushed.</sentence>
			<sentence num="44">“However, I’m very glad to see you have completely preserved all your independence of mind and even your gaiety,” he said with a rather unpleasant look.</sentence>
			<sentence num="45">“That is, you’re inwardly gnashing your teeth in vexation because I’m not crushed and humiliated,” I said, laughing.</sentence>
			<sentence num="46">He didn’t understand at once, but when he did, he smiled. “I like your observations. I recognize in those words my former intelligent, rapturous, and at the same time cynical friend. Russians alone are able to combine so many opposites in themselves at one and the same time.</sentence>
			<sentence num="47">Actually, man likes seeing his best friend humiliated before him; friendship is mostly based on humiliation; and that is an old truth known to all intelligent people.</sentence>
			<sentence num="48">But in the present case, I assure you, I am sincerely glad that you are not crestfallen. Tell me, do you intend to give up gambling?” “Oh, devil take it! I’ll give it up at once, as soon as… ” “As soon as you win? So I thought.</sentence>
			<sentence num="49">Don’t finish–I know you said it inadvertently, and therefore spoke the truth… Tell me, besides gambling, is there nothing that occupies you?” “No, nothing… ” He began testing me. I knew nothing, I hardly ever looked at the newspapers, and in all that time I had positively not opened a single book.</sentence>
			<sentence num="50">“You’ve turned to wood,” he observed, “you’ve not only renounced life, your own interests and society’s, your duty as a citizen and a human being, your friends (all the same you did have them), you’ve not only renounced any goal whatsoever apart from winning, but you’ve even renounced your memories.</sentence>
			<sentence num="51">I remember you in an ardent and strong moment of your life; but I’m sure you’ve forgotten all your best impressions then; your dreams, your most essential desires at present don’t go beyond “Enough, Mr. Astley, please, please don’t remind me,” I cried in vexation, all but in anger.</sentence>
			<sentence num="52">“Know that I’ve forgotten precisely nothing; but I’ve driven it all out of my head for a time, even the memories–until I’ve radically improved my circumstances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="53">Then… then you’ll see, I’ll rise from the dead!” “You’ll still be here ten years from now,” he said.</sentence>
			<sentence num="54">“I’ll make you a bet that I’ll remind you of it, if I live, right here on this bench.” “Well, enough,” I interrupted him impatiently, “and to prove to you that I’m not so forgetful of the past, allow me to ask: where is Miss Polina now?</sentence>
			<sentence num="55">If it wasn’t you who bought me out, then it must have been her.</sentence>
			<sentence num="56">Since that time I’ve had no news of her.” “No, oh, no! I don’t think she bought you out. She’s in Switzerland now, and you will give me great pleasure if you stop asking me about Miss Polina,” he said resolutely and even crossly.</sentence>
			<sentence num="57">“That means she’s wounded you badly as well!” I laughed involuntarily.</sentence>
			<sentence num="58">“Miss Polina is the best being of all beings most worthy of respect, but, I repeat, you will give me great pleasure if you stop asking me about Miss Polina.</sentence>
			<sentence num="59">You never knew her, and I consider her name on your lips an insult to my moral sense.” “So that’s how it is!</sentence>
			<sentence num="60">You’re wrong, however; and, just think, what else am I to talk to you about except that?</sentence>
			<sentence num="61">That’s all our memories consist of.</sentence>
			<sentence num="62">Don’t worry, by the way, I don’t need any of your innermost secret matters… I’m interested only in Miss Polina’s external situation, only in her present external circumstances.</sentence>
			<sentence num="63">That can be said in a couple of words.” “If you please, provided that these couple of words will end it all.</sentence>
			<sentence num="64">Miss Polina was ill for a long time; she’s ill now, too.</sentence>
			<sentence num="65">For some time she lived with my mother and sister in the north of England.</sentence>
			<sentence num="66">Six months ago her granny–that same crazy woman, you remember–died and left to her personally a fortune of seven thousand pounds. Now Miss Polina is traveling with the family of my sister, who has since married.</sentence>
			<sentence num="67">Her little brother and sister were also provided for by the granny’s inheritance and are studying in London. A month ago the general, her stepfather, died of a stroke in Paris.</sentence>
			<sentence num="68">Mlle Blanche treated him well, but managed to transfer everything he got from the granny to her own name… that, it seems, is all.” “And des Grieux?</sentence>
			<sentence num="69">Isn’t he also traveling in Switzerland?” “No, des Grieux is not traveling in Switzerland, and I don’t know where des Grieux is; besides, I warn you once and for all to avoid such hints and ignoble juxtapositions, otherwise you will certainly have to deal with me.” “What!</sentence>
			<sentence num="70">despite our former friendly relations?” “Yes, despite our former friendly relations.” “A thousand pardons, Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="71">Excuse me, however: there’s nothing offensive or ignoble; I don’t blame Miss Polina for anything. Besides that, a Frenchman and a Russian young lady, generally speaking–that is such a juxtaposition, Mr. Astley, as neither you nor I can resolve or understand definitively.” “If you will not mention the name of des Grieux together with the other name, I would ask you to explain to me what you mean by the expression ‘a Frenchman and a Russian young lady.’ What sort of ‘juxtaposition’ is it?</sentence>
			<sentence num="72">Why precisely a Frenchman and a Russian young lady?” “You see, you’ve become interested. But this is lengthy stuff, Mr. Astley. Here you have to know a lot beforehand. However, it’s an important question–ridiculous as it all is at first sight.</sentence>
			<sentence num="73">A Frenchman, Mr. Astley, is a finished, beautiful form. You, as a Briton, might disagree with that; I, as a Russian, also disagree–well, let’s say, out of envy; but our young ladies may be of a different opinion. You may find Racine{21} affected, distorted, and perfumed; you probably wouldn’t even bother to read him. I, too, find him affected, distorted, and perfumed, even ridiculous from a certain point of view; but he’s charming, Mr. Astley, and, above all–he’s a great poet, whether we like it or not.</sentence>
			<sentence num="74">The national form of the Frenchman, that is, the Parisian, began composing itself into a graceful form while we were still bears.</sentence>
			<sentence num="75">The revolution was heir to the nobility. Nowadays even the most banal little Frenchman may have manners, ways, expressions, and even thoughts of a fully graceful form, without partaking in that form either with his own initiative, or with his soul, or with his heart; he has come into it all by inheritance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="76">In himself he may be emptier than the emptiest and lower than the lowest.</sentence>
			<sentence num="77">Well, Mr. Astley, sir, I shall now inform you that there is no being in the world more trustful and candid than a good, clever, and not too affected Russian young lady.</sentence>
			<sentence num="78">A des Grieux, appearing in some sort of role, appearing masked, can win her heart with extraordinary ease; he is of graceful form, Mr. Astley, and the young lady takes this form for his very soul, for the natural form of his soul and heart, and not for clothing that has come to him through inheritance.</sentence>
			<sentence num="79">To your greatest displeasure, I must confess that Englishmen are for the most part angular and graceless, while Russians have a rather keen ability to discern beauty and to fall for it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="80">But to discern the beauty of a soul and the originality of a person–for that one needs incomparably more independence and freedom than our women, especially young ladies, possess–and in any case more experience.</sentence>
			<sentence num="81">And Miss Polina–forgive me, what’s said can’t be unsaid–needs a very, very long time to decide that she prefers you to the scoundrel des Grieux.</sentence>
			<sentence num="82">She will appreciate you, will become your friend, will open all her heart to you, but even so in that heart will reign the hateful blackguard, the nasty and petty moneygrubber des Grieux.</sentence>
			<sentence num="83">This will even persist, so to speak, out of obstinacy and vanity alone, because the same des Grieux once appeared to her in the aureole of a graceful marquis, a disenchanted liberal, who (supposedly!)</sentence>
			<sentence num="84">ruined himself helping her family and the lightminded general. All these tricks were uncovered afterwards. But never mind that they were uncovered: even so, give her the former des Grieux now–that’s what she wants!</sentence>
			<sentence num="85">And the more she hates the present des Grieux, the more she pines for the former one, though the former one existed only in her imagination.</sentence>
			<sentence num="86">Are you in sugar, Mr. Astley?” “Yes, I’m a partner in the wellknown sugar refinery Lowell and Co.” “Well, so you see, Mr. Astley.</sentence>
			<sentence num="87">On one side there’s a sugar refiner, on the other–the Apollo Belvedere.</sentence>
			<sentence num="88">{22} All this somehow doesn’t hang together. And I’m not even a sugar refiner; I’m simply a petty gambler at roulette, and was even a lackey, which is certainly already known to Miss Polina, because she seems to have good police.” “You’re bitter, that’s why you talk all this nonsense,” Mr. Astley said coolly, having pondered.</sentence>
			<sentence num="89">“Besides, there’s no originality in your words.” “I agree!</sentence>
			<sentence num="90">But that’s the horror of it, my noble friend, that all these accusations of mine, however outdated, however banal, however farcical–are still true!</sentence>
			<sentence num="91">You and I still never got anywhere!” “That’s vile nonsense… because, because… be it known to you!” Mr. Astley pronounced in a trembling voice and flashing his eyes, “be it known to you, ungrateful and unworthy, petty and unhappy man, that I have come to Homburg especially on her orders, so as to see you, have a long and heartfelt talk with you, and report everything to her–your feelings, thoughts, hopes and… memories!” “It can’t be!</sentence>
			<sentence num="92">Can it be?” I cried, and tears gushed from my eyes. I couldn’t hold them back, and that, I believe, for the first time in my life.</sentence>
			<sentence num="93">“Yes, unhappy man, she loved you, and I can reveal it to you, because you’re a lost man! What’s more, even if I tell you that she loves you to this day–why, you’ll stay here all the same! Yes, you’ve ruined yourself.</sentence>
			<sentence num="94">You had certain abilities, a lively character, and were not a bad man; you could even have been of use to your country, which has such need of people, but–you’ll stay here, and your life is ended. I’m not blaming you.</sentence>
			<sentence num="95">In my view, all Russians are that way, or are inclined to be that way.</sentence>
			<sentence num="96">If it’s not roulette, it’s something else like it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="97">The exceptions are all too rare.</sentence>
			<sentence num="98">You’re not the first to have no understanding of what work is (I’m not speaking of your peasants).</sentence>
			<sentence num="99">Roulette is for the most part a Russian game.</sentence>
			<sentence num="100">So far you’ve been honest and would sooner go to work as a lackey than steal… but I’m afraid to think what the future may hold. Enough, and farewell! You, of course, need money?</sentence>
			<sentence num="101">Here are ten louis d’or for you, I won’t give you more, because you’ll gamble it away anyway. Take it, and farewell!</sentence>
			<sentence num="102">Take it!” “No, Mr. Astley, after all that’s been said now… ” “Taaake it!” he cried. “I’m convinced that you are still a noble person, and I’m giving it to you as a friend can give to a true friend.</sentence>
			<sentence num="103">If I could be certain that you would give up gambling right now, leave Homburg, and go to your own country–I would be ready to give you a thousand pounds immediately to start a new career.</sentence>
			<sentence num="104">But I precisely do not give you a thousand pounds, but give you only ten louis d’or, because whether it’s a thousand pounds or ten louis d’or at the present time is perfectly one and the same to you; all the same–you’ll gamble it away.</sentence>
			<sentence num="105">Take it, and farewell.” “I’ll take it, if you’ll allow me to embrace you in farewell.” “Oh, with pleasure!” We embraced sincerely, and Mr. Astley left.</sentence>
			<sentence num="106">No, he’s wrong! If I was sharp and stupid about Polina and des Grieux, he is sharp and hasty about Russians. I’m not talking about myself. However… however, meanwhile that’s all not it.</sentence>
			<sentence num="107">It’s all words, words, words, and we want deeds! The main thing now is Switzerland! Tomorrow–oh, if only I could set out tomorrow! To be born anew, to resurrect.</sentence>
			<sentence num="108">I must prove to them… Let Polina know that I can still be a human being. All it takes… now it’s late, though–but tomorrow… Oh, I have a presentiment, and it cannot be otherwise! I have fifteen louis d’or now, and I began once with only fifteen guldens!</sentence>
			<sentence num="109">If you begin cautiously… –and can I possibly, can I possibly be such a little child? Can I possibly not understand myself that I’m a lost man? But–why can’t I resurrect? Yes!</sentence>
			<sentence num="110">it only takes being calculating and patient at least once in your life and–that’s all! It only takes being steadfast at least once, and in an hour I can change my whole destiny!</sentence>
			<sentence num="111">The main thing is character. Only remember what happened to me of this sort seven months ago in Roulettenburg, before I lost definitively.</sentence>
			<sentence num="112">Oh, it was a remarkable case of determination: I lost everything then, everything… I walk out of the vauxhall, I look–one last gulden is stirring in my waistcoat pocket: “Ah, so I’ll have money for dinner!” I thought, but after going a hundred steps, I changed my mind and went back.</sentence>
			<sentence num="113">I staked that gulden on Tomorrow, tomorrow it will all be over!</sentence>
		</chapter>
	</content>
</book>
